<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spiritual pilgrimage of Hierusalem, contayninge three hundred sixtie fiue dayes iorney wherin the deuoute person may meditate on sondrie pointes of his redemption. With particular declaration of diuers Saints bodies and holy places which are to be seene in the said-voyage: As also sundrie deuout praiers and meditations verie healpful to the pilgrimes: With licence.</title>
            <title>Devote manier om geestelijk pelgrimage te trekken tot het Heilige Land. English</title>
            <author>Paeschen, Jan van.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115004</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850224</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1272:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spiritual pilgrimage of Hierusalem, contayninge three hundred sixtie fiue dayes iorney wherin the deuoute person may meditate on sondrie pointes of his redemption. With particular declaration of diuers Saints bodies and holy places which are to be seene in the said-voyage: As also sundrie deuout praiers and meditations verie healpful to the pilgrimes: With licence.</title>
                  <title>Devote manier om geestelijk pelgrimage te trekken tot het Heilige Land. English</title>
                  <author>Paeschen, Jan van.</author>
                  <author>R. H., fl. 1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 173 [i.e. 174] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C. Boscard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Douai :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604 or 1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by J.H. of: Paeschen, Jan van.  Devote manier om geestelijk pelgrimage te trekken tot het Heilige Land.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: R.H. [i.e. Roger (= John) Heigham?]--STC.</note>
                  <note>Not in fact by R.H., but by Jan van Paeschen; R.H. is the translator--STC.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination. Page 174 misnumbered 173.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional calendars --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15411:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15411:1"/>
            <p>THE SPIRITVAL PILGRIMAGE OF HIERVSALEM, CONTAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge three hundred ſixtie fiue dayes Iorney, wherin the deuoute Perſon may Meditate on ſondrie pointes of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. <hi>VVITH. PARTICVLAR DECLARATION of diuers Saints bodies and holy places which are to be ſeene in the ſaid-voyage:</hi> AS ALSO SVNDRIE DEVOV'T PRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers and meditations verie healp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Pilgrimes:</p>
            <p>WITH LICENCE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15411:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15411:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing it is ſo my (Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike brother) that this preſente life is no other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge but a continuall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pilgrimage vvhich vve are to make vpon the earth: and that al the time of our life is a terme prefixed of God the Creator, during vvhich ſpace vve ought to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh this
<pb facs="tcp:15411:3"/>voiage, vvhich vvhen vve haue faithfully vvalked, vve may come to the Citie of heauenly Heiruſalem, vvhich is our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and moſt proper contrie: vvere it not great follie &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence in vs, if vve ſhould forget, or to ſay more trulie, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe, and not accompte, of the principal place of our repoſe, but like vnvviſe men rather to ſit dovvne and reſt our ſelues in the midle of our iorney, to vvit in the fillbie and durtie vvayes of this vvretched and vvicked vvorde? The trauailer or
<pb facs="tcp:15411:3"/>fote Poſt, vvhich is ordinarily hiered to goe ſome Iorney; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his iorney be longe, the the vveather fovvle, and the vvayes very vncleane, yet hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth not his voiage for the difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie he conceiues of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but knovvinge that he get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his liunige by meanes of the gaines, and that he ſhal vvel che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, and refreſhe him ſelf, vvhen he is arriued at his Inne, vvith great facilitie ſupporteth the aſperitie of the trauaile, vpon hope of the recompence vvhich he aftervvards expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth.
<pb facs="tcp:15411:4"/>VVe then (deare brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren expecting the (rovvne of) euerlaſtinge glorie, vvhich our lord hath promiſed to ſuch as loue him, ſhal vve appeare more vnvvillinge, or vvearie for the obtayninge hereof, then vve vvould be for the gayninge only of ſome temporall commoditie? Let vs behould therfore vvhat care &amp; paines our louing lord hath taken of our ſaluation; let vs learne to trauaille couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly &amp; like deuout &amp; holy pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes to follovve his ſteppes, vvho hath left vs an exſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:15411:4"/>of his bleſſed life &amp; paſſion, and ruminate in our hartes eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day aparte, ſome ſeuerall poinct therof, and after vvel to practiſe the ſame in our ſelues (for ſuch ought to be the end of al our ſpiritual exerciſes) by vvhich meanes vve may attaine to the happie end that vve deſier vvherof hauing found this litle Treatiſe of <hi>A Spiritual Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</hi> aſſuringe my ſelfe that it vvould be a thinge very agreable to al maner of deuout and pious perſons, I thought good to bring the ſame to light. Beſeechinge
<pb facs="tcp:15411:5"/>the gentle Reader to accept of this litle guift, and to reſpect more my hartie affection, then the littlenes of the thinge. The reſt I remitt to the diſpoſition of Almightie god the Creator of al thinges, vvhoſe only honnor and gloire I deſier herein, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy hartie vvel-vviller in Chriſt Ieſus R. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pilgrimage">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15411:5"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITVAL PILGRIMAGE TO HIERVSALEM.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> If thou deſireſt (welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) to be this holy Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime, thou muſt firſt by Confeſſion make cleane thy ſoule from ſinne: for it is vnpoſſible with an vncleane ſoule to receiue the grace of god, or to walke the iourney of a perfect Pilgrime.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thy ſinnes muſt be waſhed in the ſeuen effuſions of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The 1. effuſion, was his Circumciſion, to cleanſe thine hart from concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and al thoughtes of carnalitie.</p>
            <p>The 2. effuſion, when he did ſweate
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15411:6"/>water &amp; blood in the Garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. to purge thee from al Ire, and wrath.</p>
            <p>The 3. effuſion, was his whipinge to heale thee from al Slouth and Idel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
            <p>The 4 effuſion, his crowninge with Thorne, to ſuppreſſe thy Pride.</p>
            <p>The 5. effuſion, the ſtrippinge of his garments which cleaued faſt to his B. body, for to cure thy Auarice.</p>
            <p>The 6. effuſion his naylinge to the Croſſe hande and foote and ſayinge. I thirſt; to heale thy Gluttonie.</p>
            <p>The 7. effuſion the peircinge of his ſide, to purge thy hart from Enuie, hatred, and malice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly thou muſt prouide in thy Purſe good ſtore of Coyne, eſpecially of fine gould, for that it is light of cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adge. This gould is gotten by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and worthy, receauing of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The 1. Purſe thou muſt put this gould in, muſt be a firme faith againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15411:6"/>al aſſaultes of thine enimies; out of which Purſe thou muſt diſtribute li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally by true Loue and thankefulnes.</p>
            <p>The 2. Purſe muſt be filled with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, the which thou muſt chiefly keepe to defray thine owne expences, leaſt if thou want thereof, thou periſhe by the way for hunger.</p>
            <p>The 3 Purſe it to be filled with al ſortes of vertues and out of this thou muſt, ſpend liberally a bout the profit of thy neighbours (whether they be in this life or departed hence) by the workes of mercie both bodely and ghoſtly. Keepe ſafe theſe Purces in the wallet of meekenes, faſt Lockt with the keye of humilitie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, thy Apparel muſt be ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as our Sauiours was, beinge kinge of glorie, deſpiſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>for thy ſelf, as Chriſt did him ſelf in his life and death.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Thy Hatte muſt be Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thy Superiours, as Chriſt was to his Inferiours, in his Coronation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15411:7"/>
Sixtly, Thou muſt be ſhodde with the Shoes of ſtraight Conſideration, with deſier of following the life and ſteppes of Chriſte and his Saintes, markinge wel the difference of thy wayes from theirs.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, Thou muſt carry with thee the wallet of a pure Conſcience, and cleane harte, which thou art to beg of thy Sauioure by feruent prayer.</p>
            <p>Ayghtly, Thou muſt haue in thy hande the ſtaffe of the Croſſe, with which thou muſt alwayes ſtaye vp thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, Proceed with bleſſing thee, <hi>In the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holie Ghoſt:</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the aide of the glorious virgin Mary to be thy helpe in this Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. Pray to thy holy Angel, and to the Sainte who is thy Patrone.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Daily comende thy ſelf to god with the remembrance of thy Apparr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15411:7"/>
Accompany thy ſelf with heauenly company that they may ſhew thee the way, and ayde thee in al thy diſtreſſes, and comfort thee.</p>
            <p>Conſideringe it is almoſt impoſſible, for a Pilgrime to goe a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fallinge. Thou ſhalt recollect the Seauen fallinges of Chriſte our Lord, takinge one of them for euery Day in the weeke.</p>
            <p>The 1. the fallinge of our Lord being taken, when they haſtned him to paſſe ouer the water of Cedron.</p>
            <p>The 2. the fallinge of our Lord in the Streete being ſent from Pilate to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod and back againe, thruſt and thron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Iewes.</p>
            <p>The 3. the fallinge of our ſweete Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer with his face vpon the Steppes in Pilates houſe.</p>
            <p>The 4. his fallinge after his ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge thorough his extreame debilitie and weaknes.</p>
            <p>The 5. in his voiage to the Mount of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15411:8"/>Caluary, fallinge Seauen ſondry times to the earth by the way vnder the heauie burthen of his Croſſe.</p>
            <p>The 6. fallinge was when ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainly he was throwen downe vpon the Croſſe, and moſte Lamentably haled and ſtretched forth therupon.</p>
            <p>The 7 fallinge, when he was nayled, lifted vp, and let ral in to the mortice of the Croſſe. With a moſte ſtronge torture and ruful paine to al his holy members.</p>
            <p>And for that a Pilgrimes repaſt is often times on greene hearbes, thy Meate muſt be the ſeauen leaues which came forth of the mouth of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when he grewe and was fixed on the holy Tree of the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>The 1. leafe, o father forgeue them: here pray for meekenes, be ſlow to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The 2. leafe, this day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe: here pray for the forgeuenes of thy ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15411:8"/>
The 3. leafe, behold thy mother: here pray for diuine aſiſtance neuer to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from god.</p>
            <p>The 4. leafe, my God my God why haſt thou forſaken me? here pray for helpe and comfort of god in al thy Diſtreſſes, and that he neuer forſake thee, eſpecially in the hower of thy death.</p>
            <p>The 5. leafe I Thirſt: here pray for an earneſt deſier &amp; thirſt of the loue of god. With a feruent &amp; holy honger, worthely to receaue the B. ſacrament.</p>
            <p>The 6. leafe, It is finiſhed: here pray for fortitude to laboure and perſeuer faithfully to the end in our Lords holy ſeruice, and in thy true eſtate and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>The 7. leafe, O father in to thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des I comend my ſpirit: here pray for the worthy offeringe vp of thy ſoule at the hower of thy death in to the handes of thy Redeemer.</p>
            <p>For thy Drinke in the Tauernes, thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15411:9"/>ſhalt finde in the the Sellers of our Sauiour that wyne maketh glad the hart of man. Which be the ſeauen ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the blood of our Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The 1. effuſion his Circumciſion, here pray for the circumciſion of al ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie, and to be filled with the ſweete dew of a pure and innocent life, and perfectly to be cleanſed from luſt and concupiſcence.</p>
            <p>The 2. effuſion, in ſweating water &amp; blood; here pray to forſake al c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the loue of this wretched world.</p>
            <p>The 3. effuſion, in his whiping: here learne to reioyce in abſtinence &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>The 4. effuſion, In his Coronation: pray to reioyce in nothing but in the Croſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The 5. effuſion, In plucking of his garments: pray to pluck away from thee al old infirmities which haue long cleaued faſt vnto thee, &amp; the loue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15411:9"/>of al tranſitory thinges, that thy ſoule may be perfectly adorned with the garment of diuine loue.</p>
            <p>The 6 effuſion, In his nayling: here pray to haue a firme conſtancie in the Catholike faith.</p>
            <p>The 7. effuſion, In the peircing of his Bleſſed hart: here pray to receaue worthelie before thy departure the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>This Pilgrime muſt haue alſo, a Tent for the night: which may be the ſeauen ſorrowes of our Bleſſed Lady.</p>
            <p>The 1. ſorrow to heare old Simeon ſay, that the ſword of ſorrow ſhould pearce hir hart here pray for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of trew knowledg and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of thy ſinnes, and compaſſion for the ſame.</p>
            <p>The 2. ſorow, when ſhe fled by night in to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of Egipt. and here pray for patience in al thy tribulations.</p>
            <p>The 3. ſorowe, when ſhe had loſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and could not til three Dayes find
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15411:10"/>him againe: here pray that thou neuer leeſe his grace, but euer find it againe.</p>
            <p>The 4 ſorow, when Ieſus was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeng his Croſſe: here pray that thou maieſt willingly carry the Croſſe of Chriſt al the dayes of thy life.</p>
            <p>The 5 ſorow, when ſhe ſaw hir ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hanginge on the Croſſe, and comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge hir to his diſciple: here pray ſo to liue in this world that his holy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be not voide &amp; fruſtrate in thee.</p>
            <p>The 6. ſorow, when Chriſt was let downe in hir lappe from the Croſſe being dead: here pray to haue grace to receiue with fruite the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to haue the benifit of euery Maſſe.</p>
            <p>The 7. ſorow, when Ieſus was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſhe returned to Hieruſalem. pray that thou maieſt euer haue Ieſus abidinge in thy hart, and haue compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of our bleſſed Lady.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The lenght of this Iorney:</hi> This ſpiritual voyage is deuided in to Three hundred
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15411:10"/>ſixtie fiue dayes Iorneyes, which is for euery day in the yeare, one medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: to the end thou maieſt not be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent one hower euer in any day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge likewiſe in minde al the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid neceſſaries, to wit thy Aparel, Thy Purſe, thy Staffe, thy Diet, thy loginge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From London, or the like place:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the 1. day, Meditate of God, that he is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible, the begining and endinge of al, the fountaine of al goodnes, and abone al to be honored, loued, and magnified</p>
            <p>For the 2 day, meditate how god hath created the Angells ful of glory to praiſe him, and for the ſauegard of his creatures.</p>
            <p>For the 3. day, meditate how god made heauen and earth, and al that in them is, with in the ſpace of ſeauen dayes.</p>
            <p>For the 4. day, Mediate, of the ioy of the Angells in the creation of man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15411:11"/>
For the 5. day, Meditate of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Adam and Eue, and of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> placinge in Paradiſe, and what Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commanded them.</p>
            <p>For the 6. day, meditate of the Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Adam and Eue out of Paradice, and now Adam liued in this world nine hundred thirtie yeares in Pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, labouring for his bread with the ſweat of his browes.</p>
            <p>For the 7. day, Meditate of the diuine councel in heauen for the Deliueringe of mankind from the captiuitie of the deuil wherinto he fel thorough ſinne; and of the vnion togeather of Gods <hi>Iuſtice, and Peace, Mercie, and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the 8. day, Meditate of the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the holy Trinitie touchinge the ſaluation of mankinde.</p>
            <p>For the 9 day, meditate vpon the amiable leaue that our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt tooke of his father in heauen, and of al the celeſtial court, and of the wordes which his father vſed at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15411:11"/>
1. Saing, Goe my ſonne, goe, &amp; bringe man hither to vs that he may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from damnation euerlaſting.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Goe My ſonne in to al miſerie, Goe out of al glorie with out any maner of conſolation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Goe that thy pure humanitie, be ſubiect to thy diuinitie.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Goe like a kinge to whom ſodainly ſhal be done al princely honor.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Goe my only childe, that thy inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie may ſatisfie for the faultes and offences of al men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Goe and remember al thy paines and torments to come, to the end they may be the more greueous vnto thee.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Goe and I wil breake and cut the courſe of thy life in thy floriſhing youth.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Goe and I wil giue the ſworde in to thy enimies handes, with ful power to doe to thee whatſoever they wil.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Goe and endure the moſt cruel death and looke for no comfort at al of thy father.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15411:12"/>
10 Goe and accompliſh entirely by workes, whatſoeuer my holy Prophets haue ſpoken of thee before in wordes.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Goe my welbeloued ſonne, and make partakers both the good &amp; the euil of thine ignominius and ſhamful death, that by true repentance they may receiue it.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Goe and ſuffer, that thy death and paſſion may be ſo ineſtimable, for the which no man can euer yelde vnto thee ſufficient and condigne thankes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The eternal vvord of the father anſwered and ſaid, I am readie and vvil be obedient euen vnto the death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 1 day, Meditate how the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed virgin Mary was conceiued of Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim and Anna, after their great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deſpiſing in reſpect of their ſterilitie.</p>
            <p>The 1. day Meditate of the ioyful natiuitie of our lady the ſacred virgin Mary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the great comfort &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation hir parents receaued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15411:12"/>
The 12. day, Meditate of the Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of our Lady in the Temple being but three yeares of age, where ſhe mounted alone the fiftene Steppes or degrees with out the help of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and liued there vntil ſhe was four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene yeares olde.</p>
            <p>The 13. day, Meditate how or Lady was eſpouſed to Ioſephe when ſhe was fortene yeares of age, and retorned to Nazareth vnder the garde of holy Ioſeph.</p>
            <p>The 14. day, Meditate of the Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saint Iohn Baptiſt, which was ſhewed to Zachary by the Angel Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel.</p>
            <p>The 15. day, Meditate on the cries of the holie fathers in Limbo, for the comming of our bleſſed Sauiour.</p>
            <p>The. 16 day, Meditate how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel Gabriel receiued commandement from the holy Trinitie, to goe to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, to the habitacion of this ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate virgin, and to deliuere vnto hir
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15411:13"/>this great Embaſſage.</p>
            <p>The. 17. day, Meditate of the great ioy of the Angel Gabriel hauinge take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the forme of a fair young man to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w himſelf in the preſence of our Lady.</p>
            <p>The. 8. day Meditate and behould the maner of Salutation which the Angel vſed to our bleſſed Lady, ſainge <hi>Aue gratia plena, haile ful of grace &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 19. day, Meditate how this pure and moſte chaſte virgin was afraid at the Aparition of the Angel: and of hir prudent queſtions which ſhe vſed, and how in the end ſhe humbly yealded hir conſent.</p>
            <p>The. 20. day, Meditate on the ſacred Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ception of our Lady, by the meanes and workinge of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The. 21. day, meditate vpon the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite bountie of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt God and man, how it pleaſed him to be lodged nine mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes in the wombe of the glorious vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary, as in a moſt ſacred Cabinet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15411:13"/>
The. 22. day, Meditate on the wond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful ioyes, and ſpiritual ſweetnes which our Lady felt during nine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes wherin our Redeemer repoſed in hir virginal wombe.</p>
            <p>The. 23. day, Meditate on the louing regarde, &amp; reuerent reſpect the Angel had of our Lady duringe the ſaid ſpace.</p>
            <p>The. 24 day, Meditate how preſently our Lady roſe and went to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Iudea to viſit Saint Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, &amp; to ſerue hir.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſsing by Trent you may viſite the body of S. Simeon which is there entyre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25. daie, Meditate how ioyful theie were at their meetinge, and of the amiable Salutacions which paſſed betwene the mother of the kinge of glorie, and S. Elizabeth.</p>
            <p>The 26. day. Meditate of the ioyes of S. Iohn Baptiſt how he was purified &amp; ſanctified, being yet encloſed in his mothers wombe.</p>
            <p>The. 27. day, Meditate how our Ladie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15411:14"/>taried three monethes in the houſe of Zacharie, and ſerued Elizabeth not with ſtandinge the ſonne of Elizabeth was to become Precurſor, and ſeruant to the Sonne of our Ladie, yet did ſhe ſerue hir with al humiliue.</p>
            <p>The 28 daie, Meditate of S. Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts Circumciſion, and how Zacharie recouered his ſpeech, which before he loſt when the Angel declared vnto him the Conception of his Sonne.</p>
            <p>The 29. daie, Meditate how good Ioſeph perceauing our Ladie to be with childe, would ſecretlie haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken hir.</p>
            <p>The 30. daie, Meditate of the retorne of our Lady to Nazareth, attendinge to be there deliuered of the Sauiour of the world.</p>
            <p>The 31. day, Meditate how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel admoniſhed good Ioſeph to take vnto him the virgin Mary, and how euer after he was a faithful keeper vnto hir, vntil his death.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15411:14"/>
               <hi>At Venice you may ſee the body of S. Marck, there is the goſpel which he wrote with his owne hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 32. day, Meditate how Ioſeph and our Ladie departed from Nazareth to Bethelem beinge three dayes Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neye to be enrolled, and paye their tribute in ſigne of their ſubmiſſion to the Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Venice you may viſite the body of S. Lucie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 33. day, Meditate how our Lady and Ioſeph not finding any Lodginge in al the Citie of Bethelem, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to goe forth of the gates, in great patience retiering them ſelues in to an old ſtable, colde, and windy, fowle and vnſauorie, there to be deliuered of the kinge of al kinges, and Lord of al glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Venice you may alſo viſite the body of S. Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. day, Meditate of the ſadnes which good Ioſeph tooke in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion of the virgin Mary, to ſee hir ſo euilly entreated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15411:15"/>
               <hi>In venice you may more viſit S. Barbaraes body, and a bone of S. Chriſtophers at the croſſed friars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 35. day, Meditate of the moſt ioyful Natiuitie of our lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou maiſt at Venice viſit the body of Saint Roche.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 36. day, Meditate vpon the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble and paineful lyenge of the tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Ieſus, being naked, cryeng, and trembling with colde: begining then to confirme our peace betwene his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and vs, and of the profound reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and perfect loue our lady tooke vpon hir ſweete babe, embracing, him and tenderly kiſſing him:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou maist at Venice viſit the whole bodies of S. Zacharie. S. christine. S. Pancrace. S. Nerue. S. Gregorie Nazeanzens head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 37. day, Meditate of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles prayſing god, apearinge to the Shepheardes, and ſinging,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gloria in excelſis:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15411:15"/>
               <hi>Thou maiſt Viſite S. Helen, body in a litle Ile without venice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where one hir breast is a <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> made of the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of our lords Croſſe. Alſo there is a finger of Conſtantine hir ſonne, and a peece of Saint Mary Magdalens breaſt, and a Sanctuary of Cypres fayerlie grauen &amp; pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t here a Boatman to conduct thee to theſe holy places, Saint Andrew, or ſome other according to thy deuotion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. day, Meditate how our Lady ſwadled hir bleſſed Sonne, kiſſed him, and laid him to hir breaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou maieſt Viſit at Mucano where the Glaſſes ar made, there ar to be ſeene many of the Infants bodie, which Herod comaunded to be killed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 39. day, Meditate how our Lady gaue hir infant to ſuck of hir virginal milke, with exceedinge ioy &amp; delight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt at Padua (whilſt thou attendeſt the maſter of the Gally) viſite S. Anthonies body in the church of the Franciſ ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 40. day, Meditate how our Bleſſed Lady laied downe hir ſweete
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15411:16"/>ſonne in the manger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now goe to thy holy Angel, and deſier him to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lpe thee to a good and ſkilful Pilote, to cary thee to the holy Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The lord of this Shippe muſt be Saint Peter, to whom comende thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou muſt agree to giue the Patrone of the Gally, fiftie Ducats of gould for thy paſsage, which ar</hi> 50. <hi>paters, and</hi> 50 <hi>Aues. or ſome other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Gouernours of this shippe, muſt be Saint Paule. Saint Iohn the Euangeliſt: S. Chriſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, and Saint Nich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>las, but the Protector muſt be S. Michael, honor al theſe, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thy ſelfe vnto them, Goe with thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful frende thy holy Angel and make thy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe from henceforth, as thou haſt done in the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 41 day, Meditate diligently of the burninge loue and deſier the litle child Ieſus had to deliuer mankinde out of the miſerie and ſeruitude wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was deteined.</p>
            <p>The 42. day Meditate how the litle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15411:16"/>ſweete childe Ieſus, tooke great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of our miſeries, geuinge a piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Crie, and did ſhed teares a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to make our peace with his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, the which no man could doe but him ſelf</p>
            <p>The 4. day, pray for a god winde and ſay, <hi>Veni createor ſpiritus &amp;c.</hi> and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate how the Angelles appeared to the Shepheards.</p>
            <p>The 44 day, Here ſtrike Sayle, and ſay the <hi>Salue Regina &amp;c.</hi> and Meditate how ſpeedely the Shepheards went to Bethelem and adored the ſweete litle Babe.</p>
            <p>The 45. day Meditate of the great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rackles in Chriſts Natiuitie: God is ioyned with humanie nature his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remayneth a virgin, and faith, and humanie nature ar there accorded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather.</p>
            <p>The 46 day, Meditate of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Twelue Sibilles.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Sibilla Perſica<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Behold the Beaſt of al
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15411:17"/>the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hal be ouerthrowen, and the lord of al the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hal be borne, and the body of a virgin shal be vndefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sibilla Libica. The day ſhal come and the Lord ſhal geue light, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne with mercie (the body of his mother ſhal be the waight and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of euery one, that is ſhal be the ballaunce to weigh al our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Sibilla Cumea, he ſhal mount and riſe in the face of the virgin, and ſhe ſhal be worſhipful, cleane, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful of face. &amp;c ſhe ſhal nouriſh the Infant, and geue him hir owne mylke for meate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sibilla Eriſtria in Babilon from the higheſt top of heauen god hath bleſſed the humble of minde, and in the latter day a young Sonne ſhal be borne of an Hebrewe virgin.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Sibilla Samea. behold there ſhal come a riche man, and ſhal be borne of a poore woman, and the beaſtes of the earth ſhal worſhip him ſainge
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15411:17"/>praiſe him to the higheſt top of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Sibilla Cumana: In the laſt time ſhal be ſent from heauen a new lyne and generation.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Sibilla Heleſpoſtina. Chriſt ſhal be borne of a moſte pure virgin.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Sibilla Frigia: The moſt higheſt ſhal come out of heauen. the councel ſhal be confirmed in heauen, &amp; in the vally of the miſerable ſhal be the virgin ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Sibilla Europa. He ſhal come that ſhal trauaile beyonde the mountaines and little hilles, and he ſhal raigne in pouertie, and he ſhal haue domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in tranquilitie and modeſtie, and he ſhal come forth of a virginis wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Sibilla Tiburtina. Chriſt ſhal be borne in Bethelem, and how happie is the mother that ſhal geue him ſuck.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Sibilla Delptica. A Prophet ſhal be borne of a virgin without knowledge and copulation of man.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Sibilla Agrippa: The inuiſible
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15411:18"/>worde ſhal be taſted &amp; touched, &amp; ſhal drye like a leafe, and his beaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie ſhal ſeeme nothinge, the wombe of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal compaſſe him, and he ſhal be reiected of man, and he ſhal be borne of his mother as God, and ſhal ſeeme like a ſinner.</p>
            <p>The 47. day, Meditate of the great ioy and humble ſeruice of Ioſephe to his ſpouſe Mary, and to the bleſſed babe Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The 48. day, Meditate of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of our Lord, and the ſhedinge of his blood as an earneſt penny of his death and paſſion:</p>
            <p>The. 49 day, Meditate of the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the holy name of Ieſus, in which name whatſoeuer ſhal be aſked of his father, ſhal be graunted vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The. 50 day. Meditate how the three kinges came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> far cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries in the ſpace of 15 dayes. to adore this infant as God and man, beinge guided by a Starre which apeered vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15411:18"/>
The. 51 day, Meditate how the three kinges found the litle childe, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto him Goulde, Mir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and francumcenſe, as to true god, and true man.</p>
            <p>The. 52. day, Meditate how the three kinges admoniſhed by the Angel, returned by an other way in to their contrie, and were two yeares in their Iorney, and liued and died moſte holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſame.</p>
            <p>The. 53. day, Meditate of the great greife and ſorrowe which approached the meeke hart of the ſweete virgin, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe vnderſtood, what waite Herod laied to kil hir childe Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The. 54. day, Meditate how this Bleſſed Lady preſented hir childe in the Temple, redeeminge him againe with a couple of Turtles or Pigeons: and of Simeon and Anna.</p>
            <p>The 55. day, Meditate of the firſt dolour of our Lady by the wordes of Simeon in the Temple, wherupon ſhe ſhed teares.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15411:19"/>
The. 56. day, Meditate how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel warned Ioſeph to flee in to Egipt wherby our Ladies ſorrowe was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
            <p>The 57. day, Meditate of the haſtie flyeng of our Lady &amp; hir ſweete childe, with al diligence, by nighte thorough the wildernes. for others being but or dayes Iorney, for them a monthes iorney by reaſon they ofttimes erred. conſider with al the great periles of Theeues and murderers, their excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge wearines, and pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Seuches, vvhere Saint Heir ome in amount did his pennance, there is a Cloyſter of Saint Peter. deſier Saint Peter thy Patrone to ſet thee on land to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Sant Hierome, and</hi> 15. <hi>myles thence, is the towne of Stridonia vvhere. Saint Hierome vvas borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 58, day, Meditate of the humble and ſimple entrie of our Lady with hir babe and Ioſeph into Egipte, at whoſe entrance al the Idolles fel downe, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15411:19"/>how in Heleopolis with much adoe they got a poore Cottage and dwelt therein labouringe for their liuinge. <hi>At Zaram in Dalmacia, the auncient Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons body lieth, who made the Cantickle, Nune Dimittis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 59. day, Meditate how the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie with hir Sonne remained in I hebaida in the citie of Heleopolis vij yeares, takinge paines to earne their bread, and of the iniuries thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered of the ſtrangers of that contrie.</p>
            <p>The 60. day, Meditate how after ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares the Angel appeared to Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, and willed him to retorne in to the land of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>The 61. day, Meditate how Ioſeph roſe and went to the land of Iſrael, with great labour, difficultie, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</p>
            <p>The 62. day, Meditate how Ioſeph feared when he heard that Archelaus raigned in his fathers ſteade &amp; beinge warned by an Angel, went to dwel in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15411:20"/>Nazareth, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e alſo labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nige, and liuinge in very ſimple &amp; poore eſtate.</p>
            <p>The 63 day Meditate how our Lady nouriſhed hir childe Ieſus and brought him vp with great care and loue.</p>
            <p>The 64 day, Meditate how Ieſus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his bignes, ſerued his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother, and how he often wept vnknowing to his mother, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Raguſa the head of Saint Blaſe and hir left arme. And the Sheete vvith vvhich old Simeon tooke our Lorde in his armes. The left arme of Saint Iohn Baptiſt vvithout the vvrest. And the head of Simeon the Apoſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 65 day, Meditate how the childe Ieſus being but twelue years old, went to Hieruſalem to ſerue god, and tarried there three dayes amonge the docters, with out the knowledge of his father and mother.</p>
            <p>The 66. day, Meditate of the third dolour of our Lady hauing loſt hir
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15411:20"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne about 4 dayes, and how ſhe found him in the mideſt of the docters</p>
            <p>The 67. day, Meditate how Ieſus kept him ſelf ſecreat and ſimple, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhewinge any mirackle, vntil he was. 30. yeare olde.</p>
            <p>The 68. day, Meditate how Ieſus opened and declared to his deare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Prophecies and ſecreats of the holy ſcripture.</p>
            <p>The 69. day, Meditate how Ieſus kept him ſelf with his mother and Ioſeph poorely and in ſecreat wiſe, and how they liued and did eate together, with great ſobriety, and geueinge thankes vnto God.</p>
            <p>The 70. day, Meditate of the amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and gracious face of our Sauiour Ieſus, of the moſte comely feature of his body, and of his holy condicions, and decent demeanors.</p>
            <p>The 7. day, Meditate how Ieſus kept him ſelf ſecreat vntil he was 30. yeares of age, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding alwayes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15411:21"/>he did wonderful thinges by reaſon of his diuinitie, and obtained many things for vs of his heauenly father thorough his feruent prayer and deuotion.</p>
            <p>The 72. day, Meditate of the ſorrowe our Lady had when hir ſpouſe Ioſeph died, and gaue vp his ghoſte in to hir Sonnes handes, being but: 20. yeares olde.</p>
            <p>The. 73. day, Meditate how louingly Ieſus comforred his mother, when ſhe often wept for to conſider the paines of his paſſion, and how he exhorted hir meekely to conforme hir wil to the wil of god.</p>
            <p>The. 74. day, Meditate how the word of our lord was vpon S. Iohn Baptiſt, preachinge pennance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and cryinge in the deſart. <hi>Parate viam Domini:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 75. day, Meditate of the leaue our Lord Ieſus tooke of his dolent mother, to goe to be baptiſed, and of the virgins teares at his departinge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15411:21"/>
The. 76. day, Meditate how S. Iohn Baptiſt ſeinge Chriſt cominge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde him ſaid, <hi>Ecce Angnus dei.</hi> that is behould how like an innorent la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be he cometh.</p>
            <p>The. 77. day, Meditate how Ieſus came to Iohn to be baptiſed, and how firſt Iohn humbly refuſed to doe it, but ſeinge it was his holy wil to haue it ſo, he baptiſed him.</p>
            <p>The 78. day, Meditate how that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ieſus was baptiſed, he prayed, and the heauens opened, &amp; the holy Ghoſt came downe in the likenes of a doue, and a voice from heauen ſaid. <hi>Hic eſt filius meus dilectus.</hi> This is my wel belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne heare yee him.</p>
            <p>The. 76. day, Meditate how Ieſus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his baptiſinge, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight againſt the Deuil the enemie of mankinde: &amp; how he departed in to a wildernes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Hieruſalem and Hierico, and did conuerſe amonge the brute beaſtes, &amp; lyenge on the colde grounde many nights.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15411:22"/>
The. 80. day, Meditate how Ieſus ouercame the temptation of the Deuil, in Gluttony, vainglory, and Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and how after, the Angels came and ſhewed their ſeruice vnto him.</p>
            <p>The 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day, Meditate how the next day S. Iohn Baptiſt ſaw Chriſt come towardes Iordane, and how he ſhewed with his finger ſayinge againe <hi>Ecce Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dei,</hi> and how two of Iohns diſciples hearinge thoſe wordes, followed our Lord.</p>
            <p>The 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day, meditate how S. Andrew led Peter to Chriſt, and how Chriſt entertayned S. Peter, and the next day Chriſt caled Phillip to folowe him.</p>
            <p>The 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day, Meditate how Chriſt went to a mariadge in Cana of Galile, and how he tourned water in to wine a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his mothers requeſt</p>
            <p>The 84. day, Meditate how poorely nakedly &amp; imply Chr ſt as apareled, and how ſoberly he fed with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke the worſte to him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15411:22"/>ſelf, ſuffringe colde, heate, rayne, thriſt. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The 85. day, Meditate how Ieſus, with his diſciples being ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, went to Hieruſalem at Eaſter, &amp; with a whippe draue out the buyers and ſellers, and chaungers, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threwe their Tables, ſaying make not the houſe of my father a houſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe. <hi>Domus mea domus orationis vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabitur.</hi> My houſe ſhal be caled the houſe of Prayer.</p>
            <p>The 86. day, Meditate how Ieſus baptiſed his Apoſtles in Iordane, and S Iohn in Elim, wherat Iohns Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were ſcandalized, but Iohn wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed vnto them, not of him ſelf, but of Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The 87 day, Meditate with what feruour and charitie, our Sauiour prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vnto the people, and healed the diſeaſed, and conuerſed with them meekely.</p>
            <p>The 88. day, Meditate how humbly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15411:23"/>Chriſt compained with his Apoſtles and anſwered their rude queſtions ſweetely, and with what boldnes they walked cloſe by him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite the Churches in Candia, and in the Graye Friers, is a peece of the holy Croſſe: one of the armes of Saint Simeon the Apostle: and a peece of Saint Lawrence head: a peece of the goulden Gate. and the miter of Alexandre the Third and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Image of Saint Lukes Paintinge: and a peece of the Piller, at the which our Lord av as vvhiped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 89. day, Meditate how much wronge, and iniurious wordes our Lord had of the Iewes, for that the poore and ſimple people followed him.</p>
            <p>The 60 day, Meditate how Ieſus with his diſciples went vp in to a mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to watch and pray, to pacifie his heauenly father who was angrie with mankinde. and how in the morhinge he choſe his twelue Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:15411:23"/>
The. 91. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge in the morninge taught his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples the viij. Beatitudes.</p>
            <p>The. 92. day, meditate on the ſweete admonition of our Lord, confirming his diciples againſt tribulations, and aduerſities, comparinge them to Salt, and Light.</p>
            <p>The. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day, Meditate how Chriſt admoniſhed his diſciples to Patience, in turninge the left Cheeke to him who hath ſtroken thee on the right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Rhodes in the cheife church, where the right hand of S. Iohn Baprist with the fingers with which he baptiſed Chriſt. Alſo a peece of the Croſſe of Christ: and one of the Thornes of his Crowne, which bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h euery good friday tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and flowers, alſo one of the ſiluer peeces Christ was ſolde for. Alſo an Arme of S <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loy, an Arme of S. George S. Blaſes Ancklebone. S. Barbaras Soul: and a peece of S Clare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 94. day, Meditate how our Lord taught his diſciples the Pater noſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15411:24"/>
               <hi>You may viſite at Rhodes in the Chappel of the great maſter, the Arme of S. Anne. and a peece of S. Steuen</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 95. day, Meditate how queitly Chriſt did beare in his hart, al his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to come, not declaringe them to any of his frendes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Rhodes at S. Catharins Chappel, there is the Ringe and finger of hir, the which Chriſt eſpouſed hir withal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 96. day, Meditate how Ieſus beheld Mary Magdalen with his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful eies, and drew hir to repentance. &amp; now ſhe entred the houſe after him, and waſhed his feete with hir teares, and wiped them with the heares of hir head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Rhodes in the Hoſpital of the knightes of the Rhodes, with was taken anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>22. by the Turkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 97. day, Meditate how S Iohn Baptiſt was impriſoned and how he ſent to Chriſt, ſayinge. <hi>Tu es qui venturus es an alium expectamus?</hi> art thou he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15411:24"/>which art to come, or doe we looke for any other?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſite at Rhodes where the three holy kinges haue often bene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 98. day, Meditate on the prayſe and rewarde wich Chriſt gaue vnto S. Iohn Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viſite without Rhodes where S Iohns Head was founde there is a pleaſante fountaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 99 day, Meditate of the glorious death of S. Iohn Baptiſt and how the daunſinge damoſel, gaue his head to hir Aduoutrouſſe mother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite in Rhodes a wood where S william made his Pennance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 100. day, Meditate how Chriſt taught his diſciples not to lay vp their treaſure in the earth, but in heauen, and ſo to imbrace voluntarie pouertie.</p>
            <p>The 112 day, Meditate how Ieſus taught his diſciples not to be careful what o eate, or what to weare, but to ſeeke firſt the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>The 102. day, Meditate how Ieſus fed
<pb n="04" facs="tcp:15411:25"/>his diſciples with his ſweete wordes, when they could get no meate.</p>
            <p>The 103. day, Meditate how midely Ieſus ſhewed him ſelf towards Iudas whom he made his Steward &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge he ſhould betraye him, he much lamented him as often as he ſaw him.</p>
            <p>The 104 day, Meditate how Ieſus gaue power to his diſciples to worke mirackles, &amp; ſent them to preach two and two, as Lambes amonge woules, exhortinge them to patience.</p>
            <p>The 105. day, Meditate how Ieſus went him ſelf by Sea and by Land to preach and after cured their diſeaſes. and conuerſinge rather with the poore then with the riche, for which the Scribes &amp; Phariſes maliciouſly hated him.</p>
            <p>The 106. day, Meditate how our Sa: willingly ſuffered with patience, of the magiſtrates, and miniſters of the Temple, their mockes, diſdainful loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and preuie conſpiracies againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15411:25"/>him, condemninge him for a ſoole, and an euil man.</p>
            <p>The 107. day, Meditate how meekely our Sauiour ſuffered the docters of the Temple, who would haue put him to death but for feare of the people, and how our Lord then ſhuned the ſame for that his time was not yet come.</p>
            <p>The. 108. day, Meditatete how Ieſus was receaued in to the houſe of Martha and Mary with his diſciples: and how Mary did narrowly obſerue his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, his abſtinence, his ſobrietie in eatinge, his prudent and ghoſtly talke, and his diuine wordes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite S. Helens goulfe wher she threw one of the nayles Chriſt was crucified with al, &amp; euer ſince that Sea hath bene more calme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite Baffa where the. 7. sleepert reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 109 day, Meditate how the bleſſed Mary Magdalen followed our Lord euery where, and prouided for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15411:26"/>him, and for his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>The. 110. day, Meditate of our Lords wearines, and ſitinge at the Welle, and how he asked water of the woman of Samaria, and how his diſciples mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled.</p>
            <p>The. 111 day, Meditate this day, of the painful iorney and trauaile of our Sauiour paſſinge through the contries to preach the Goſpel, and cure their diſeaſes, ſuſtaininge in the meane time many wants, as if he had not bene the only Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viſite in that part wher S. Catharin was brought vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 112. day, Meditate how meeke and gentle our Lord was when any did diſhonor him, ſpeakinge againſt his doctrin and ſaing his workes were done by the power of the Deuil</p>
            <p>The. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day, Meditate of the great meekenes, and clemencie of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our towardes the Iewes, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he knew the great malice and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15411:26"/>enuie they bare towards him.</p>
            <p>The 114. day, Meditate of the ſweete countenance and louinge teares our Sauiour often ſhed in the Temple before the Aultar, for the finnes of the people.</p>
            <p>The 115. day, Meditate how the moſt mightie kinge of glory, the heauenly father (who could haue deſtroied al people in the world in amoment, and made others in their places) moſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>beningly, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcifully, with great patience and longe ſufferinge choſe rather for to ſee his only begotten Sonne our Sauiour Ieſus to be Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and to ſhew vs exſample of life by his owne ſteppes, and precepts, where by we might pleaſe god.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e 116 day, Meditate how Chriſt anſwered the Iewes when they brought to him in the Temple the woman taken in Aduoultrie, and how mercifully he deliuered hir</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Famaguſts, of olde Fama Coſti, of S.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15411:27"/>Katharins father kinge of Cipres: vvhere in a Chapel is one of the Hidries in the which Chriſt turned water in to wine. vi. mile from thence is the auncient Fagus, where S. Katha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim was borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 117. day, to Tyre goinge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards S. Catharins body. Meditate how as our Lord was preachinge a woman cried out ſainge, <hi>happie is the wombe that bare thee, and the papes that gaue thee ſuck.</hi> and of Chriſtes anſwere. yea hapie ar they that heare the word of god and keepe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this contrie is ſons hortorum, &amp; puten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> aquarum viuentium. In Tyre the woman of Cananie was healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 118. day, Meditate how Ieſus proued the faith of the woman of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanie, makinge interceſſion for the health of hir poſeſſed daughter, which ſhe obtained, and was alſo highly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for hir faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goinge to Acon, and thence to mount Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molus, where Elias the Prophet was. in thi
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15411:27"/>place the friers Carmalites began, and al (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that vveare a Religions Cloacke) ought to geue themſelues to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat deuotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 119. day, Meditate how our Lord did teach Nichodemus (who came to him by night) and ſaid to our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Lord and maſter, we knowe thou comeſt from god, for no man can doe theſe ſignes thou doeſt, except he be of god. how Chriſt taught him the entrance to heauen, to be by Baptiſme. and that as the Serpent was lifted vp in Moiſes time, ſo ſhal the Sonne of man be exalted, that whoſoeuer ſhal beleue in him ſhal not periſhe but haue life euerlaſtinge.</p>
            <p>The. 120. day, meditate of our Lords inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to his diſciples, not to feare them who could kil the body only, but to haue feare of offendinge him, who could caſte both body, and ſoule, in to euerlaſting fire, and that who ſo ſhal confeſſe me before men, I ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him before my father which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15411:28"/>
The 121. day. Meditate how our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer tould his Diſciples for what cauſe he came in to this vale of miſery, and to what intent he did chooſe them vnto him, ſainge, I am come to put fire in the earth, that is the fier of the holy Ghoſt, to enflame the hartes of men, and to make t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burne in diuine loue. An ſo I am come to be baptiſed with a certaine baptiſme, and how much I am troubled vntil it be perfected in me vnderſtanding by this his holy paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the which he ſo greatly thirſted.</p>
            <p>The 122. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſaid to his Diſciples, I am not come to bringe peace (meaninge temporal) in the world, but warre. and who ſo loueth his father or his mother more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, is not worthy of me, &amp; who ſo embraceth not his Croſſe with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and carieth it after me, he is not worthie of me, that is of my grace &amp; euerlaſtinge glory and he that loueth his life in this world, ſhal l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe it, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15411:28"/>he that ſhal forſake this preſent life for the loue of me, in deſpiſinge of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orldly preaſures, he ſhal keepe it, and finde it in the life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>The 124 day Meditate of the great loue and reuerence Chriſt had to his Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſaing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he that heareth you, heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me alſo. and he that recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you, receaueth me, and he that geueth you but a cup of colde water ſhal not looſe his reward. for I wil ſay at the day of Iudgment, I was a ſtraunger and Pilgrime, and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued me, I was thirſtie, and you gaue me to drinke. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Gaza Samoſon tooke the gates of the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and caried them to the toppe of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and after hauinge his eies put out and his heare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen in which conſiſted his force, he praied to god, and his ſtrenght retorninge to him a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne, he pulled a vvay tvvo of the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vvhich ſuſtained the houſe, and the vvhole houſe fallinge, he ſlevv a great nomber of his enimies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15411:29"/>
The 124. day, Meditate how Ieſus entringe into the deſert, taught his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, not far from Tiberias, when he heard that Herod had put Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt to death. not that he feared death, for that his time was not yet come, but to ſhew his elect an exſample, that it wil be beſt ſometimes, to geue place, and auoid from the wicked.</p>
            <p>The 125. day, Meditate with what great feruour, deuotione, and zeale, the humble people followed our Lord Ieſus in the deſarts to heare the word of god, and how Ieſus came downe from the mountaine, and ſweetly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued them, and alſo healed their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, both in body, and ſoule.</p>
            <p>The 126. day, Meditate how our Lord Ieſus hauinge compaſſion of the multitude of people, willed his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for to prepare them meate, namly ſpeakinge vnto Phillip, who anſwered that two hundred peniworth of bread wold not be ſufficient that euery one
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15411:29"/>might haue a little; S. Andrewe tould him of a boy, who had fiue barley loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and two fiſhes. wherupon willinge them to ſit downe he fed therwith, fiue thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d men beſides the woemen, and litle children, and they carried away twelue baskets ful of that which was left of this banquer by reaſon whereof the people glorified god, and confeſſed that Ieſus was the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that ſhould come to ſaue the world.</p>
            <p>The 127. day, Meditate how Ieſus fled, and humbly retiered him from the people when he knewe they wuold come and make him kinge, as he who refuſed wordly honor. but comminge to apprehende him to haue him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, he then moſt willingly offered him ſelf vnto them.</p>
            <p>The 128. day, meditate how Ieſus went vp alone vpon the high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of contemplation (contemning al the honors of the world) for to pray,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15411:30"/>and to render thankes to his heauenly father for al his benefits.</p>
            <p>The 129. day, Meditate of the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of fiue loaues, and of Chriſtes bleſſinge of them, by the meanes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof vntil this preſent hower, al ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual hartes, are greatly refreſhed, and made ſtronge, and how it is he who nouriſheth al creatures.</p>
            <p>The 130. day, Meditate how our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour-ſaid, I am the true bread which came downe from heauen, and am ſent in to the world to gene euerlaſtinge life, he that cateth me ſhal not hunger euerlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>The 131. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſaied vnto the Iewes. The bread which I wil geue is my fleaſh for the life of the world, by the which al holy ſoules ſhal be enriched, with al graces and heauenly vertues.</p>
            <p>The 132. day Meditate of the wordes of Ieſus, he that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, dweleth in me,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15411:30"/>and I in him, not as your fathers haue eaten manna in the deſert &amp;. are dead, but he that eateh-this bread ſhal liue for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Al Heliopolis our Lady vvith Ieſus remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vvhen he did flie vvith him in to Egipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 133. day, Meditate of the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the groſ headed people, and Diſciples, and how mildely he ſpeake vnto his Apoſtles ſainge, &amp; wil ye goe and leaue me alſo? To whom Peter anſwered Lord to whom ſhal we goe, ſeing thou haſt the wordes of eternal life? we beleue that thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the huinge god, and Ieſus ſaid againe, I haue choſen you twelue and yet one of you is a deuil but fear you not, a bide in your faith, and I wil abide in you, and fortifie you, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe you in al vertue</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Cayrus, or Babilon vvhere the Sow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>den is of vvhom the vſe is to obtaine a paſport and licence to viſit the holy places: comende thy ſelf and thy cauſe to the Patriarche Ioſeph,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15411:31"/>vvho vvas Lord of Egipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 134. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſaid If the the graine of corne fal not one the ground, and die not, it remaineth alone; but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruite. meaninge thereby the increaſe of the goſpel, after his paſſion. <hi>You may viſite a Garden in Cayrus of the Souldaine vvhere balme grovveth, and vvhere are</hi> 7. <hi>fountaines vvher vvith the Garden is vvatered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 135. day, Meditate how Ieſus went twiſe with his Diſciples to pray, and repoſe him ſelf. and how the people followed him, and brought to him many ſick, and poſeſſed of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and he healed them al, and how they prayſed him, and gaue thankes vnto God.</p>
            <p>The 136. day, Meditate how Ieſus fe †. 4000. men, with 7. loaues, and a few litle fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes, and of the 7. baskets of fragments which did remaine. Alſo how the people did loue him &amp; would
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15411:31"/>haue taried ſtil with him if he had not commanded them away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may paſſe tovvards the red Sea vvhere kirge I harao vvas drovvned and ſo to mount Sinai vvhere. S. Katharins body lieth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 137 day, Meditate how Ieſus was tempted of the Phariſes who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a ſigne of him from heauen, to whom our Lord made this anſwere, you knowe and can iudge the times without ſignes from heauen, but the tokens of my comminge fortolde by the Prophets you cannot know, by reaſon of your vnbeleife and malice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may Take Ship to paſſe the red Sea vvhere if you finde none ready, pray to Moyſes, that vvith his Rodde he vvil open the vvay to you, or to the holie Prophet Helias that vvith his Cloake denidinge the vvaters, he vvil make paſſage for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 138. day, Meditate how Ieſus asked his diſciples whom doe men ſay that I am, and they anſwered ſome ſay thou art Iohn Baptiſt ſome one of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15411:32"/>Prophets. but Peter laid, thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing god.</p>
            <p>The 139. Meditate vpon the ſweete comfortable wordes which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gaue to S. Peter ſaing, bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas, for that fleaſh &amp; blood hath not reuealed this vnto thee, but my father which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>The 140. day, Meditate how Ieſus caled al his Apoſtles by name, and how he gaue ſpecially preuiledge to S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to them, ſaing whatſoeuer ye ſhal looſe on earth, ſhal be looſed in heauen, and whatſoeuer ye ſhal binde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n earth, ſhal be bound in heauen.</p>
            <p>The 141. day, Meditate of the heauie newees which our Lord Ieſus fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toulde vnto his Apoſtles aſcendinge to Hieruſalem, how that he was to be betrayed; mocked; whipped; and crucified from which when S. Peter diſſwaded him he ſaid, goe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinde me Satan, for thou vnderſtandeſt not the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15411:32"/>things which are of god, but of men.</p>
            <p>The 142. day, Meditate how Ieſus commanded his Apoſtles to imprint theſe wordes firmely in their hartes, that the Sonne of man ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied in to the handes of ſinners, and how they ſhould kiſle him. and that he would riſe againe the third day, and of the ſorowe his Diſciples had, to heare tel of his death and departure.</p>
            <p>The 143. day, Meditate how Ieſus went towardes the mount of Thabor, and how he tooke with him Peter, Iames, and Iohn, and aſcended with them to pray, &amp; how whilſt he prayed, he ſequeſtred him ſelf from al earthly cogitations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may Viſite the Cloiſtre of Saint Ka<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin at the foote of the mount Sinai vvhere in the Church nighe the high Aultar, is a Tobe of white marble vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſteps to aſcende it, vvhere in the bones of S. Katharin virgin and Martir lieth. there is the sheete (al bloody) vvhere in the Angels lapped, and caried the body of this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15411:33"/>bleſsed Martir. there is alſo the wedhir holye head to the Pilgrimes. now is it neceſſary that our pilgrime ſtirre vp his denotion, and vvith al inſtamed affection, inuocate the aſiſtance of this bleſſed virgin and martir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 144 day, Meditate how our Lord whilſt he prayed, was transfigured be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his three Diſciples, and of the brightnes of his face which ſhined like the ſonne, and the whitenes of his garments as the ſnowe.</p>
            <p>The 145. day, Meditate how Moiſes and Helias appeared gloriouſly with Ieſus vpon the mount Thabor, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould al his paſſion which he ſhould ſuffer in Hieruſalem.</p>
            <p>The 149. day, Meditate how Moiſes comminge from Limbo from the holy fathers, and Helias from Paradice ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtre, reioyced to ſee the Sauiour of the world our Lord Ieſus Chriſt to be come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the great compaſſion they had to ſee that glorious face, how it ſhould be defiled &amp; ſpitte on, buffeted and mocked.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15411:33"/>
               <hi>You may paſſe from the church of S. Katharin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to the mountaine of Moiſes: at the Iron gate as you goe out S. Kath. church, is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of vvater, vvhich iſſued forth of the Rocke, vvhen Moiſes vvith his Rod ſtrooke the ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 147. day, Meditate how Ieſus on Mount Thabor ſhewed his diuinitie to his Diſciples, and how by diuine illumination they knewe Moiſes and Helias, whom they neuer ſawe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite goinge vp the hil of Moiſes, the Cloiſtre where our lord appeared to the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes, vvhen they fled from their Cloiſtres for feare of the ſauage beaſtes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 148. day, Meditate of the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of S. Peters wordes, Lord, ſaid he, it is good for vs to dwel here, if it pleaſe thee let vs make three Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> deſierous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that his maſter might continue ſtil in ſuch glorie.</p>
            <p>The 149. day, Meditate how Moiſes and Helias departed awaye from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ieſus, and of the bright cloude that came and couered them, and of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15411:34"/>voice forth of the clowde, ſainge, this is my welbeloued Sonne in whom I am wel pleaſed heare yee him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite deſcend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the mountaine, the church of fortie martires, in the valley vvhere the children of Iſrael daunſed about the goulden calfe, and Moiſes brake the Table of ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 150. day, Meditate how the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples hearing that diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce from heauen, fel downe to the ground for feare.</p>
            <p>The. 151. day, Meditate how Ieſus came to his Diſciples and ſweetly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted them, and touched them, ſaing, ariſe and be not afraid. and liftinge vp their eies, they ſawe none but Ieſus alone; and as he went downe from the mountaine, he charged them to tel this viſion to no man vntil he were riſen vp from death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you paſſe from the Monkes of S Katherin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to the deſert, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dayes Iourney longe, prouide for ſtore of victual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:15411:34"/>
The 152. day, Meditate how Ieſus deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending the mountaine, his Diſciples asked him, how is it that the Scribes ſay, that the Helias muſt come before the Sauiour of the world? and Ieſus anſwered Helias is come (meaninge S. Iohn Baptiſt) but they beleeued him not, but did vnto him whatſoeuer they would, and ſo ſhal the ſonne of man alſo be crucified.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>53. day, Meditate how Ieſus deliuered many poſſeſed with diuels, &amp; reſtored them whole to their fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and parents.</p>
            <p>The 154. day, Meditate how the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples demanded of Ieſus, why the diuels went out ſo hardly and would not obey them ſometimes. and how Ieſus anſwered, if yee had as much faith as a graine of muſtard ſeede, you ſhould commande this mountaine to remoue, and it ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obey you and if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhal be impoſſible vnto you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15411:35"/>
The 155. day, Meditate how Ieſus is come in to this world for the loue of thee, the hundred ſheepe which was loſte, and ſtraied away, forſakinge the .99. which at the Angels in heauen, he is come to ſeeke ſinners, &amp; to cal them to repentance, and gladly to cary them on his proper ſhowlders, by mercie and grace, in to the kingdome of heauen. and that there is greater ioy in heauen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one repentant ſinner, then of .99. iuſte.</p>
            <p>The 156 d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, Meditate of the parable of the prodigal ſonne, of his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion returninge to his father, and his receauinge in to fauour againe.</p>
            <p>The 157. day, Meditate how Ieſus taught his diſciples to forgiue their enimies and S Peter demandinge how often, Chriſt ſaid, I ſay not .7. times, but .70. times .7. times.</p>
            <p>The 158. day, Meditate how the younge man asked our Sauiour what he ought for to doe, to obtaine the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15411:35"/>kingdome of heauen. and Ieſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, keepe the comandements. The younge man replied that he had kept them al from his youth, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what more ought to be done: and Ieſus anſwered if thou wilt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, goe and ſel al thou haſte and giue it to the poore, and come and followe me.</p>
            <p>The 159. day, Meditate deuoutly of the three counſels of the holy ghoſte 1. voluntarie pouertie 2. perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence 3. chaſtitie and perpetual conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie.</p>
            <p>The. 160. day, Meditate of volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarie pouertie how S. Peter ſaid, for him ſelf and his bretheren, Lord we haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, what re-ward ſhal we haue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ieſus anſwered verely yee that haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, and followed me, yee ſhal ſit on xij ſeates, and iudge the xij tribes of Iſrael, and ſhal receaue a hundred foulde in this life, and in the world to come life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:15411:36"/>
The 161. day, Meditate now Chriſt compared the kingdome of heauen like to a good huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dman, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho hiereth workmen into his vineard for apenny a day to labour vntil the ſittinge of the ſonne. which ſheweth this life is to be led in Pennance of vs vntil our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath.</p>
            <p>The 162. day, Meditate how Ieſus councelled al men to make them fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of their Mam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>on of iniquitie, that when they are gone hence, they may receaue him in to euerlaſting Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nackles.</p>
            <p>The 163. day, Meditate how ſpiritual and deuoute perſons, may doe their Almes, by preachinge, teachinge, and prayinge for others, who are in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie or in Purgatorie.</p>
            <p>The 164 day, Meditate how ten lep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs came vnto our Lord Ieſus, and liftinge vp their voice ſaid, Ieſus Maſter haue mercie on vs, &amp; Ieſus anſwered them, goe, ſhew your ſelues to the Preiſtes.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15411:36"/>and how one being a Samaritane, and perceauing that in the way he was made whole, he retourned and gaue thankes to god. Whom Ieſus recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</p>
            <p>The 165. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſaid, many are called, but fewe are choſen: Seneca ſaith no man cometh to death more gladly, then he who prepareth him ſelfe for death.</p>
            <p>The 166. day, Meditate how the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nte of Ieſus, the mother of the two ſonnes of Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bedee, asked of Ieſus that one of hir ſonnes might ſitte on his right hand, &amp; the other one his left hand when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came in his kingdome, and of the anſwere our Lord gaue vnto hir.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Hebron vvhich ſtandeth in the valley of Mambre there you may ſee Abrahams houſe, vvhere ſittinge vnder the Oake, he ſaw three parſons cominge to warde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him. Tres vidit, &amp; vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rauit he ſavv h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, &amp; vvorsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ped one, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w he receaued the Angels into his houſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15411:37"/>Ioſua first came to Hebron vvhen he vvent to be we the land of promiſe, before that the children of Iſrael entered. kinge Dauid alſo did reignein Hebron vij yeare, and a halfe. In Hebron are the ſepulchers of Abraham, Iſaac. and Iacob, and of their vviues Lot alſo is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 167. day, Meditate how Ieſus taught his Diſciples to flie from al pride, ſainge, the kinges and Princes of the world beare rule ouer them, and they are caled <hi>Benefici,</hi> but amonge you it ſhal be otherwiſe, and he that wil be greateſt ſhal be ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the others, like as the ſonne of man is not come, to be ſerued, but to ſerue al.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite Hiericho vvhich vvas a ſtronge Citie, and vvas miraculouſly taken by Proceſsion. vvhere Rahab and hir family vvas ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 168. day, Meditate of the voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good Zacheus, &amp; of the words which he had with our lorde, and our lorde with him. That the ſonne of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15411:37"/>man is come to ſaue that which is loſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Hiericho You may ſee the houſe of this Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus, vvho vvent vp into a vvilde ffiggetree to ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſus, into vvhoſe houſe our lorde vvent. bere Pilgrimes vvere vvonte to reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 169. day, Meditate how vpon the mountaine by Hiericho Chriſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the blinde man who ſate begginge by the way, and cried, Ieſus ſonne of Dauid haue mercie one me.</p>
            <p>The. 170. day, Meditate how God the father declared, that in Ieſus his Sonne was his delighte, and the fulnes of al grace, which we ought to aſke, &amp; to remember our promiſe in Baptiſme, &amp; that Chriſt baptiſeth with the holy ghoſte. <hi>Hic eſt filius meus dilectus ipſum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite.</hi> this is my welbeloued Sonne heare yee him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſite the Riuer of Iordana vvhich deuideth Galilee, from Idumea, and Baſan, &amp; faleth vnder the grounde and riſeth in Euel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame vvhere is the ſepulcher of Iob, and thence is the end of it into the dead Sea, vvhich is the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15411:38"/>place vvhere the fiue cities, Sodome, Comorah. &amp;c ſtoode vvhich vvere burned vvith fier and brimſtone from heauen On the right ſide of the riuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth vvife vvas turned into a Piller of Salt. thereby is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch of Saint Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist. and there by Ieſus vvas baptiſed in Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane where the Pilgrimes comonly do vvashe them ſelues. There god vvas heard ſpeake from heauen, and the holy Gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte vvas ſeene come downe in the likenes of a Doue, and al the holy Trinitie vvas preſent in that place. The children of Iſrael paſsed drie foote through the bottome of the vvater. Helt alſo did ſtrike the vvater vvith his Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k and raſſed thorough the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>footed, and Helizeus alſo. &amp; Naaman the Sirian vvas he I him ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times in the riuer, and vvas healed of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Leproſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 171. day, Meditate of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours faſtinge, prayers, teares, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and lyenge on the ground many nightes, ſolitarie, without conſolation or comfort of any man, amonge the wilde beaſtes, for thy loue and iuſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; haue compaſſion of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:15411:38"/>therfore, ioyne thy harte to his, and followe his ſteppes by auſteritie of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this deſart vvhere our lord faſted.</hi>40. <hi>Dayes, and</hi> 40. <hi>nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, caled the mountaine of Quarantine, vvhere the Diuel tempted him, there vvas an Heremitage. and there is the vvater vvhich vvas made ſweete by the prayer of Elizeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 172 day, Meditate how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſaluted the glorious virgin Mary of hir Conception: and how after ſhe nouriſhed our Lord in Narazeth. of his humble conuerſation with al men &amp; how beinge kinge of heauen he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to be caled Ieſus of Nazareth, and beinge the Sonne of god, was named the Sonne of a Carpenter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At the mountaine vvhere the diuel caried our lord, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> winge him al the kingedomes of the vvorld, and ſainge he vvould giue them al to him if he would fal downe &amp; worship him Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee thorough the coutries, vntil yee come to Silo vvhere god appeared firſt to Samuel in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15411:39"/>Heli his dayes, and ſo to Suhar, by vvhich is the fountaine of Samaria: one of Hieroboams goulden Calues, vvere erected thereby at Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel. In this Citie of Suhar, Dina the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Iacob vvas rauish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, by occaſion where of, Iacobs ſonnes ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>we al the inhabitants of Sichem The mountaine of Garizen is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereby, vvhere the Samaritanes vvere wonte to pray. On Garizon Abraham offered his ſonne Iſaac to god. In the plaine is the Ceſterne, in to which Ioſeph vvas th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owen before his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren ſoulde him. And thence is the vvay to Samaria vvhich vvas the ſeate of the kinge of the ten Tribes of Iſrael, and is now caled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>baſte. Saint Iohn Baptiſte vvas buried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here but he vvas beheaded at Macherouda. Iulian the Apoſtata cauſed his body to be burnt, and his ashes to be hurled in to the riuer of Iordane, but the finger vvher vvith he pointed, ſainge behould the lambe of god, remayneth yet entire. Saint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecla caried his finger beyonde the Alpes. The Emperour cauſed the head to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebaſte, vvhere it vvas incloſſed in a vval &amp; found al bloody vvrapped in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ete, &amp; caried,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15411:39"/>to Saint Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſters church in Rome, the hinder parte of the head, vvith the neather lawe and Chinne, and ſome of his ashes, and the dishe in vvhich his head vvas carried. Thence by diuers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of Galilee, vntil you come to Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vvhere the Angel ſaluted our bleſſed Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. day Meditate how our lord Ieſus called his Diſciples, and on the ſea of Gallie taught them. preached to the people, and cauſed Peter to walke on the water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At the montaine of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abor ther is a place ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſchoole of god, where Chriſte taught his Diſciples. There Christe vvas transfigured before his Diſciples. At the foote of Thabor Melchiſidec kinge of Salem (vvhich is Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem) met Abraham vvhen he had ouercome the</hi> 5. <hi>kinges, and delinered his brother Lot, from captiuitie. One mile farther is the mount Hermon; on vvhich vva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcituate the citie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>im vvhere Ieſus raiſed the vvidowes ſonne as he vvas caried to be buried vij miles from Nazareth is the place vvhere Lamech vvho vvas blinde, ſlew Caine, vvho had killed his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15411:40"/>brother Abel. Thence yee goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer the ſea of Tibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>as; in to the lande of the Gerazins. vpon the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Galilee, Ieſus walked on ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>foote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 174 day, Meditate how Ieſus healed the poore man which had bene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſick .8. yeares, biddinge him to take vp his couche and wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and of the murmoringe of ſhe Phariſes becauſe he tooke vp his bed on the Saboth day. and how Ieſus findinge the man in the Temple, ſaid vnto him. <hi>Goe and, ſin no more, leaſt any vvorſe happen vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Tiberias is the Table vpon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which our lord &amp; Sauiour did eate with his Diſciples at Ema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and not far of, is the place where our Lord fed v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand men, with v. loaues and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fish. beſides there is Sephorin, where S. Anne our Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es mother vvas buried: and beneath that is the houſe of the Centurion. in returninge you come to Ceſaria Phillip, whence kinge Dauid had many goodly Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars tovvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the buildinge of the Temple in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruſalem. The land of Promiſe is in enght, from Dan to Berſabe, that is north and South</hi> 29. <hi>miles
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15411:40"/>of Combardie &amp; from Hierich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to lapha</hi> 90. <hi>miles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 175. da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Meditate ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Lord in the Temple of Hieruſalem reſtored to ſighte the man who was borne blinde, with anointinge his eies with ſpittel and duſt, bidinge his goe waſhe in Silo. and of the great murmoringe and detraction of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At lapha the hauen towne vvhere you lad.</hi> 117. <hi>iorneye, caled of lapha the ſonne of Noe, and the aun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ients cittie in the vvorld. it is caled lopp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Ackes, Peter ſaw the sheete vvith al kinde of beastes let downe from heauen: and raiſed Tabitha from death there ſay Tedeum, &amp; Salue Regina for thankſg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge to our lord vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ſofely conduct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d thee thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> longe iorney here as lapha thou muſt ſend to them ſter of the Gality, to ſend to the lord of the cuntrie for thy ſafe conduct to paſse to Hieruſalem, vvho is vvonte to come vvith ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat company vvel apointed, and bring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h vvith him the reuerend Garden of the ffriers of Sion, and one, or two of his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15411:41"/>vvhoe inſtructe the bretheren bovv they must vſe them ſelues in viſitinge the holy places. firſt he asketh of they haue licence of the Popes holines to viſit the holy ſepulcher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for it is exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication to do it vvithout his leaue: but if by chaunce any become vvithout it, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den may abſolue him, and licence him alſo. firſte he vvarnet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>that they doe no-reuerence the one to the other, leaſt therby the Turkes doe knovve their eſtate. 2. That vvhea they g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to viſite the holie places, they goe. 5. or. 6. toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for feare of the infidelles. And that they neither goe nor ride ouer the Seapulchers of the Infid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lles. If they be iniured in thoſe places by the Mahumetanes, or runnegate Chriſtians they muſt not reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge it but ſuffer al for Chriſts ſake, vvho ſuffered much mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in that place for vs. That euery one purge his conſcience, and giue himſelf to deuotion This done they goe to the lord of Hie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſalem, vvho taketh al their names, and ſirnam's. The ſpiritual P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lgri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e muſt cal to minde his baptiſme and profeſsion, and to renew his promiſe in Baptiſme, and from hene forth to purge his conſcience, withful purpoſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15411:41"/>of amendment, and to take patiently. al detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and aduerſitie. Their nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s being regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, they are put into sellers by the ſea ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vntil horſes, Aſses, Mules, and Camels be prouided for them to ride on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 176. day, Meditate how out lord raiſed ſazarus from death beinge. 4. Dayes dead, when Ieſus cried Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus come forthe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Rama vvhere is a church of our Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; an Hoſpital for Pilgrimes founded by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Duke of Burgundie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 177. day, Meditate how the Iewes ſate in councel oftentimes how they might put Ieſus to death, ſuch was their hatred and malice. And how Iudas came to them and ſould his maſter for. 30. pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At lidda or. Diſpolis, vvhere Saint Peter healed Eneas of a palſie. There Saint George ſuffered his martirdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 178. day, Meditate how Chriſt ſent two of his Diſciples fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bethpage to Hieruſalem to feten the Aſſe and hir
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15411:42"/>fole: how he did ride vpon the ſilly beaſt: and how he was receaued of the people ſinginge <hi>Hoſanna filio Dauid,</hi> how behouldinge the Citie, he wept vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, foreſeeinge the miſeries which ſhould fal on it for killinge of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Caſtel of Emaus a myle from Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, vvhere Chriſte did eate after his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 179. day, Meditate how Ieſus from Palme Sonday, to the wenſday folowinge, was daily in the Temple, preachinge to the people, where the Scribes and Phariſes had laied diuers to wacth &amp; repehend him, and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and they forbad that any one ſhould geue him bread or drinke, in ſuch ſorte that euery night he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to goe to Be haine to take his foode, where he remayned al wenſday at the requeſt of his mother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At mount S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo (vvhereby vvas the citie of Gabaon) on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s mounte the Arke of god was buried. There on this mountaine you may ſee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15411:42"/>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 180. day, Meditate how Ieſus tooke his leaue of his doleful mother at Bethaine, vpon Maundie Thurſday in the morninge, to goe to Hieruſalem. And how our Lady requeſted. 4. thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. if it were poſſible that he might not ſuffer. 2. that ſhe might ſuffer for him. 3: that ſhe might die before him. 4. that he might die a milde kinde of death. and how he paſſed a longe by mount Caluarie. and how he ſent two of his Diſciples before him, to prepare his Paſſouer, geueing them this token to followe a man carienge a pot of water in which houſe they prepared the Paſche.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Silo you shal come to Hieruſalem, and before you enter the citie, the names of the Pilgrimes ar regiſtred againe, vvhere remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber againe vvhe thy name vvas firſt geuen thee, and vvhat promiſe thou madeſt in Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 81. day meditate how many ſad and ſorowful ſteps, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſus tooke
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15411:43"/>thorough the ſtreetes of Hieruſalem, &amp;c how his colour changed paſſing thorough the ſtreetes, whilſt he went there meditatinge of his bitter paſſion and torments, and how his moſte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood ſhould be troden vnder their vile feete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the citie of Hieruſalem, and firſt to the holy Tempie of the holy Sepulcher: before the Temple is a fair ſquare place, in vvhich is a fair ſquare ſtone, hauing many croſſes grauen there on: in this place our lord fel vvith his heaui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Croſſe on his showlders: here the Pilgrims creepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuoutly and kiſſe this ſtone from thence they goe to the church doore to the holy Croſse, the Sepulch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and the place vvhere our Lady did ſit houldinge hir ſonne in hir armes beinge taken from the Croſse. In comninge forth of the Temple. is sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed the place, vvhere our lord Ieſus did appeare in the day of his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the. Maries, three Thence as you goe to Saint Ieames his church (vvhere he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vvas be headed) is the place vvhere our Ladie dweled and deed. There is a fair great stone in that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15411:43"/>place, from vvhence our Ladie vvas caried being dead, to the valley of Ioſaphathy the Apoſtles. Thence you goe to Sion to the Hoſpital of the Rhodes, and thinke that the graye friars that lead thee, are Saint Francis, Saint Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Saint Anthony of Padua, Saint Barnard &amp;c. whom thou must ſalute with ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out prayers, Nere that is the place, vvhere S. Iohn (the vvelbeloued Diſcipleand Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt.) celebrated Maſſe before our Bleſſed Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, day, meditate of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful humilitie and benignitie of out Lord Ieſus, on Maundy thurſday at night, peparing him ſelf to be offered, the true Paſchal lambe, for the ſinnes of al the world: and to eate the Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with his Diſciples and Iudas, who now had ſould him for mony to the Iewes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goinge from the Hoſpital of Sion, you are to goe to the Cloister barefoote, and barehead ſaing the pſalme.</hi> Fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum eius in mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bus Sion. <hi>vvith a collect, that our lord vvill
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15411:44"/>aſiſte thy prayers in that place and going vpp 7. ſteppes yee enter the Cloiſter of sion, vvhere is a Table ſet vvith bread and vvine, for thoſe to take thereof vvho vvil: then the Eriars ſinge the high Maſſe, vvhich ended they goe to warde the holy Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 183. day, Meditate how humbly our Sauiour prepared him ſelf to waſhe his Apoſtles feete firſt he did of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and gyrded him ſelf with a Towel, kneeled and waſhed euery one of their feete, euen the feete of Iudas with the ſweat of his browes, and teares of his eies, ſhewinge vs a ſpecial exſample of brotherly loue and humilitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may viſit the place vvhere the Paſchal lambe vvas eaten: returninge to the church quior, on the right hande is the place vvhere Chriſt vvashed the feete of his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The. 184. day, Meditate how Ieſus after the waſhinge of his Apoſtles feete ſate downe, and dranke to them al, in token of his loue. and how he gaue his moſte precious body and blood to his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15411:44"/>Apoſtles to eate and drinke, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his painful death and paſſion, and to Iudas alſo, whom in ſecreat he warned of his ſinne &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in token that there is nothinge hidden or vnknowen to him. And of S. Iohn reſtinge on his breaſt to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a ſecreat toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a morſel dipped &amp; geuen to Iudas, he opened who it was that ſhould betray him. and how af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the receauinge of the morſel the deuil entred into Iudas and imediataly goinge out, he ioyned him ſelfe with the enimies of Chriſt, and prepared armoure &amp; weapons to take our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Sauiour. And how Ieſus tould Saint Peter that he ſhould deny him of the ſermon Chriſte made to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ful of loue. how he roſe, ſaid grace, and praied for his D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſciples and folowers, And how our Sauiour went againe from that houſe acom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pained with his Apoſtles, teaching them, vntil he eame to the mount of Oliuet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15411:45"/>
               <hi>Thou shalt againe viſit theſe holy places in the Church and Quiare vvith great deuotion and affection, and eſpecially the bleſſed body and blood of our lord, vvith ſome deuoute praier. And before thou g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the church thou shalt goe downe</hi> 8 <hi>ſteppes vnder the Qutar, vvhere is the Parlour vvhere the Apoſtle: hid them ſelues, and vvhere Ieſus after his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction entered (the doores being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t) and ſaid to his Diſciples</hi> Pax vobis, <hi>peace be vnto you. In which place is alſo a Chappel vvhere Ieſus appeared after to S. Thomas, and shevved him his vvoundes to feele, vvhen Thomas vvor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him ſaid.</hi> Dominꝰ &amp; Deus meus <hi>my Lord and my god. In the Quiare of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, is aſquare Chappel, vvhere is an Aultar. vvhere the Apoſtle, receaued the holy ghoſte, here thou art to ſay thy Beades, or ſome prayer to the holy ghoſte As thou goeſt out of the Church thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>halt viſit the place vvhere the last ſupper vvas made ready Not far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence vvas S. Stephen firſt buried. And nere there kinge Dauid made the <hi>7.</hi> pſalmes. Behinde that, at the foote of mount sion, vvas the citie of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15411:45"/>Dauid, &amp; there are the ſepulehers of the kinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Iſrael. There is a peece of the Piller to the vvhich our lord was bound and vvhipped, this place hath an Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doore, of the vvhich the Mores keepe the key, and before the doore is a place vvhere Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour vvas vvonte to ſit and preath, to his mother, and his Diſciples. And there is the ſtone on vvhich our Lady fate at the ſermon, Not far thence our Lady vvas vvonte to prey, Therby is the place of the Apoſtles aſſembly, vvhen they held their Councel, before they vvet thorough the vvorld. and in this place Saint Mathevv vvas choſen in Iudas ſteade. To wards the valley of Ioſphat, is the place vvhere S Paule kett the garments of thoſe vvho ſtoned S. Stephen, Thence is the goulde gate through vvhich Chriſte came rid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge of the Aſſe on Palme Sonday. And belowe vnder the vval, is the vall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of Ioſaphat, ouer the brooke Cedro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer the bridge. Alſo beyonde, at the foote of sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the Sepulcher of our Lady, fortie ſteppes vnder the ground. In the midle of thoſe ſteppes is the Se pulcher of Saint Anne, vvhich Saint Helin tranſlated to Conſtantinople
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15411:46"/>and there vvas buried Ioachim our Ladies Father, and Ioſeph hir huſband. At the Sepulcher of our Lady, is a fair church deepe vnder the grounde, vvhich is ſo, by meanes of the ruines of Hieruſalem. The Sepulcher of our Lady is couered vvith a stone of mount Sinai brought by the Angels. ſay here thy Beads in honor of the virgin Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 185. day, <hi>To the garden of Oliuet.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus came with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to the mount of Oliuer, &amp; tooke Peter, Iames, and Iohn with him, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge the others belowe in the garden, &amp; how he went further alone, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſadd, and ſaid vnto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that they ſhould watch and pray leaſt they enter into temptation and how he went a ſtones caſt farther, and praied to his heauenly father.</p>
            <p>The 186. day, <hi>At the Caue vvhere Chriſt pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the firſt time,</hi> Meditate of the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and teares of our bleſſed Sauiour of his trembling, falinge on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and praying to his heauenly father the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15411:46"/>firſt time ſaying, father if it be poſſible let this cup of my bitter paſſion paſſe, alwayes reſerued the health of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. then appeared to him al the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paines he was to ſuffer, and he wept bitterly. and how then he found his Diſciples ſleepinge for ſadnes. and. how he awaked them ſweetly &amp; ſaid to S. Peter. Simon ſleepeſt thou? the ſpirit indeed is wilinge, but the fleaſh is weake.</p>
            <p>The 187. day, <hi>VVithin that Caue vvhere Chriſte praied the ſeconde time.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus went back from his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, without hauing any comfort, and praied in like maner as before. he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to tremble for anguiſhe of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts he ſaw were to come on him and came againe to his Diſciples ſleeping, and awaked them, and retorned againe without hauing any comfort of them.</p>
            <p>The 188. day, <hi>VVithin the Cauerne vvhere Chriſt praied the third time.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus went the third time to pray
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15411:47"/>laden with extreame ſorrowe, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge him ſelf in forme of a Croſſe with great affection of loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that he might ſuffer his paſſion for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of the world, praying moſte harely as afore. and thereupon he did ſweat water and blood for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe of death, which diſtilled on the ground. And how the Angel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared and comforted him with the redemption of the worlde. His drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes were Nintie ſeauen thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, three hundred, and ſine, as after was ſhewed by a reuelation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15411:47"/>
            <head>PRAYERS FOR THE VOIAGE OF THE CROSSE, WHICH ARE IN NOMBER. 15. VVHICH you may ſay at any other time.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>THE 1. STATION.</head>
               <p>BY the bitter anguiſh which thou enduredſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Oliuer, when thou dideſt ſweate water and blood, aſiſte me to reſigne my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to thy holy wil (ſpecially at the hower of my death) and to ioyne and vnite my ſelfe to thee.</p>
               <p>The 189. day, <hi>From the Caue to the Garden of Oliuet, vvhere Iudas came to kiſſe him, and betraye our Sa:</hi> Meditate how Ieſus roſe ſorowfully from his prayers, and came to his Diſciples, and bid them reſt, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15411:48"/>ſate downe a while with them, &amp; then by &amp; by willed them to riſe. and went and met Iudas, and the reſt with lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, and weapons, and how Iudas kiſſed our Lord, being the token he gaue his enimies to knowe Ieſus from the others The ſorrowe of our Lord for this ingratitude of Iudas ſayinge, <hi>Amice ad quid veniſti?</hi> frend wherfore co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thou? betrayeſt thou the ſonne of man with a kiſſe? &amp; how then he went forwardes towardes the multitude.</p>
               <p>The 160. day, <hi>In the Garden of Oliuet.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus came before his enimies, to whom he ſaid <hi>quem queritis?</hi> whom ſeeke yee? how they fel to the grounde. And how S. Peter drewe his ſworde, and cut of Malchus right eare and how Ieſus healed Malchus eare, by touching of it and comaunded Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to put vp his ſworde. &amp; of Chriſtes wordes to the multitude, <hi>haec eſt hora veſtra,</hi> this is your hower, yealdinge him ſelfe willingly into their handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:15411:48"/>
The 191. day, <hi>In the Garden of Oliuet.</hi> Meditate how the ſonne of god, was deliuered into the handes of ſinners, without helpe or comfort from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how they bound his holy handes, &amp; how meekely he ſuffred them. how they beate him, and hurled him on the grounde, and abuſed him moſte vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanouſlly. and of the great diſcomforte of his Diſciples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may viſit in this mountaine the place vvhere the Angel appeared to Saint. Thomas, Apoſtle and brought vnto him our Ladies girdel. A Litle higher is the place where our Lord wept on Hieruſalem. Higher is the place where the Angell brought our Ladie tidings of her death, and a branche of Palme from paradice to be caried before her. Againe higer is the Caſtele of Galile where the Angell toulde the woman of Chriſts reſurrestion. Thence to the rounde Church, where our Lord ſtoode when he aſcended vp to heauen. And the figure of his ſacred feete are there printed in a ſtone, by which it appeareth that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15411:49"/>he looked to wardes the North, when he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Going downe is the houſe of</hi> S. Pella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, <hi>the common ſinner where she did her pennaunce. On the North ſide thereof is the place where the Apoſteles made theire Creede. Alſo the place where our Lorde ſate being wearie, when his diſciples a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked him of the day of Iudgment. Thereby is a houſe where our lord did teach his diſciples the</hi> Pater noſter <hi>Going downe is the place vvhere our Lady did ofte vſe to pray, after the death of hir ſonne. Lower vnder a Rock, is the ſepulcher of Abſalon; vpon that ſepulcher the Infidels paſsinge by, caſte ſtones, &amp; ſay curſed be Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon vvho perſecuted his father, and al that doe the like, be curſed euerlastinglie. There is a litle bridge ouer Cedron, where the Iewes drewe our Lorde being bound, thorough the vvater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 192. day, <hi>To the Riuer of Cedron.</hi> Meditate vpon the pitteous drawinge and pullinge of Ieſus, from the mount of Oliuet in their furie thorough the water of Cedron, into the citie, &amp; ſo to howſe of Annas.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:15411:49"/>
Nere Cedron is the Caue whereunto S. Iames did flie, &amp; would not eate nor drink vntil he knewe of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lord. Nere to this towards Bethanie, is Iudas the Traitors houſe. Aboue within the bridge towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Sion, is the Temple of Salamon, high and rounde, and couered with leade, in to which Chriſtians cannot enter. There by this Temple is the Rocke of Bethel where Iacob ſlept and ſaw the Ladder from heauen, where vppon the Angels went vp and downe. There alſo Dauid ſawe the Angel ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de which killed the people. There our Lord preached, and pardoned the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which was taken in adultrie. There the Angel appeared to Zacharie father of S. Iohn Baptiſte. Melchiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deche here offered bread and wine to Abraham, in figure of the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Vpon this Rock Dauid kneeled, when he ſaw the Angel ſtrike the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and praied for pardon, and would
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15411:50"/>haue builte the Temple, our god forbad Dauid to build it, becauſe he had killed vrias. but Salomon did burlde it. Out of this Temple our Sauiour did caſte them that did buy and ſel. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Temple, and the Aultar, was Zacharie the ſonne of Barachias, ſlaine. Nere to this is <hi>Probatica piſcina.</hi> Wher the market of ſheepe for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, were ſoulde. Where when the Angel had troubled the water, who euer went firſt downe and waſhed therein, was healed here Chriſte healed him who had bene ſicke 38. yeares. In this Temple our Lord was preſented, when holie Simeon tooke him in his armes. Higher is the place where S. Peter wept bitterly for his den venge of Chriſte. Yet higher on that hille, is the place, where the Iewes would haue ſtaied the corps of our Ladie. when ſhe was caried to be buried, but they were by mirackle hindered. Hard by is the houſe of Annas.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:15411:50"/>
                  <hi>Againe in the howſe of Annas (which is now a Churche) there dwel Greeke Monkes who ar Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. day, Meditate how Ieſus was led like a Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife to Annas houſe, who skornfully entreated him, and was maruelous glad, thinkinge now to be reuenged on him. queſtioninge of his Diſciples, and his owne Doctrine. to whom Ieſus anſwered, I haue alwayes taught openly in the Sinagoge and the Temple, aske not me, but aske them who haue heard me one of the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (vnthankful Malchus as ſome thinke) ſtrake him with a greueous blowe vpon the face, in ſo much that Chriſt fel to the ground greatly bleedinge at the noſe and the mouth, and riſinge ſaid in milde maner: if I haue ſpoken il breare witnes, but if I haue ſpoken wel, why doe you ſtrike me?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The. <hi>2.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Lord who ſufferedſt thy ſelf to be bound &amp; taken viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of thoſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15411:51"/>miniſters of malice, and to be haled, and trailed to Annas houſe, there to be skorned, abuſed, and iniuriouſly ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that the blood followed. I beſeeche thee to pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al my ſinnes whatſoeuer paſte, and ſo bridel my tounge and my ſpeech, that I may ſpeake nothinge to the offence of my neighbour, but that euer my mouth and hart, may ſownde forth thy prayſe, and with al patience, to ſuffer detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; reproches, with humilitie and conſtancie in al aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the houſe of Caiphas. which is now a Church in which is the ſtone which was laied at the mouth of the ſepuliber of our Lorde, which is very great and beaute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 104. day, Meditate how Annas ſent Ieſus bound in great deſpite, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with thoſe peruerſe miniſters to Caiphas houſe, where by the way he receaued many ſore blowes, ſpittinges, and mockeries, there beinge gathered al his mortal enemies who deſiered his
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15411:51"/>death and findinge not any ſufficient cauſe ſought for ſalfe witnes againſt him and not findinge theſe neither, Caiphas adiured Chriſt to tel him if he were the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God. Where vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus anſwered. Thou haſte ſaid, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge you ſhal ſee the ſonne of man ſit on the right hande of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the cloudes of heauen, wheir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon Caiphas ſaid <hi>Blaſphemauit</hi> he blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemeth, and asked the reſt what they thought, they anſweared he is worthy of death.</p>
               <p>The 165. day, meditate what great ſorrow Chriſt had in his ſoule when he was ſo iniuriouſly handled accuſed mocked, haled, beaten and ſtriken, in the houſe of <hi>Caiphas</hi> and how they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his face &amp; bid him deuine who it was that ſtrooke him. And what great ſorrowne he receaued when his Apoſtle denied him three times. And how he looked on Saint <hi>Peter</hi> with his mercifull eies. At the which S. <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15411:52"/>remembring him ſelfe, leauing his Lord in the handes of the wicked, he went out, and wept bitterly.</p>
               <p>The 196 day, to a darke Chappelle on the South ſide of the quiet called the priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, Heare Ieſu was put in priſon, and garded with 8 of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and cruelleſt villanies that might be founde, who did manie villanies and tormentes vnto him, al that night. And there is a piller of ſtone to the which our Lord was bounde. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate with what incomprehenſible pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and humilitie, the great mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arcke of heauen and earth ſuffered all theſe villanies and iniuries, being al that night in the handes of theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and wicked men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O My Lord, by the exceſſiue loue which conſtrained thee to be bounde, to the end to looſe me from the bondes of ſinne, geue me grace ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to forgette thy great loue, and the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15411:52"/>iniuries which thou ſufferdeſt this night; and that I may ſuffer paciently all wronges done vnto me, that I may driue all ſlouthfullnes from me, and exerciſe al workes of charitie towards my neighbour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVithout the Chapel is the place. Where</hi> S. <hi>Peter denied his maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. 197. day. <hi>From Caiphas houſe, to the houſe of</hi> Pilate. Meditate how in Caiphas houſe Ieſus heard the wicked Iewes conſulting to accuſe him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pilate as a traitor to the Emperor a breaker of their lawes, and a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor againſt God. And how in the morning they led him againe into the councell houſe, and aſked him if he were Chriſt; which he denied not. Where vpon they bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his handes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, &amp; put Iron chaines about his neck. And our good Lord, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſelfe thus to be led through the ſtreetes, whither they woulde, vntill he came to Pilats lodging.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:15411:53"/>
                  <hi>Behinde the houſe of Caiphas is the feild caled</hi> Haceldama, <hi>or</hi> Ager ſanguinis, <hi>vvhich vvas bought for</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>penece, for the burial of ſtraungers, beinge</hi> 50 <hi>foote broade, and.</hi> 72. <hi>foote longe. In this is a Seller hauinge nine hoales, thorough vvhich th y let downe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rie ſtians that die there. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udas repented him. Alſo in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t pit is a deepe hoale, vvhere the Apoſtles hid them ſelves vvhen Ieſus vvas take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> In that place is a faire tree vvith a ſeate to ſit on, vvhere it is ſaid that Eſay vvas hanged by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeles, and vvas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wen a ſonder thorough them del of his body, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> head, vvith a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſawe Belovv in a great valley, is</hi> Nata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria Siloe, <hi>vvhetherour Lorde bid the man that was blinde from his natiuitie, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he. Lower is the valley of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſaphat: In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> valley is the ſelcher of our Lady, cut out of a Rocke, couered vvith a marble ſtone fairvvrought, in the midel of a faire church Entringe into Hieruſalem by</hi> Potta S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erquilinia, <hi>in a litel ſtreete there by, is the houſe of Ioachim vvhere our Lady vvas borne. This place the Infidels abuſe for one of their Temples. Alitel
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15411:53"/>beneath is</hi> Probatica Piſcina, <hi>vvhere the vvood of the holy croſſe for many yeares vvas bide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. here the ſick receiue their health. A little lower is the houſe of thoſe vvho led Chriſte to Pilate, beinge.</hi> 300 <hi>in nomber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 198. day. <hi>In Pilats houſe.</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate how meekely Ieſus ſtoode before Pilate, hearing al paciently which he was accuſed of, and that which was feigned againſt him the chiefe Preiſtes, for enuie and malice. the falſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for bribes and mony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the people for flatterie and fauour of their rulers. and of the ſorrowe of harte ſweete Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus had for them, and for Iudas the Traitor, whom he knew to be damned euerlaſtingly, by reaſon of his diſpaire, although he confeſſed his fault, and reſtored back the mony.</p>
               <p>The 199. day, <hi>Before Pilate in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel houſe.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Meditate how Pilate tooke Ieſus from the Iewes into the councel houſe, and asked of him if he were the king of the Iewes. Ieſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15411:54"/>my kingdome is not of this world &amp;c: Pilate ſaid. then thou art a kinge. Ieſus ſaid, I am. &amp;c. Pilate ſaid what is truth: &amp; ſo roſe, &amp; went forth to the Iewes, and ſaid, I finde no fault in this man. The Iewes ſaid he hath ſtirred vp the people, teachinge from Galilee to this place. Pilate hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe he was of Herods Iuriſdiction, ſent him to Herod who was then in Hieruſalem.</p>
               <p>The 200. day, <hi>From Pilate to Herods houſe</hi> Meditate how Ieſus as led to Herod with greate confuſion, who was glad of his comminge, for many a day he longed to ſee Ieſus becauſe of his mirackles Herod asked Ieſus many queſtions but our Lorde anſwered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge. Herod and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s courte deſpiſed Ieſus, cloathinge him in white, and fendinge him back to Pilate as a foole.</p>
               <p>The 201. day, <hi>From the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alace of Herod, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the houſe of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>late<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ditate how Ieſus came back to Pilate w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th great paine
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15411:54"/>and confuſion, whom Pilat excuſed that nether he nor Herod had found any thinge in him worthie of death, thinkinge to let him goe free in ſteede of Barrabas. But the Iewees choſe Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas, and required Ieſus to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p>The. 202. day, <hi>To the Chappel where Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late cauſed Ieſus to be whipped.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus benige ſtripped naked, tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and was aſhamed. How meekely he ſuffred him ſelf to be bound to a Piller and whipped ſo terribly, that from the top of his head, to the ſoale of his foote, no parte of his fleaſh remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whole, and ſeemed ſo weake that he was not able to ſtande, receauinge 624. laſhes with roddes and whippes.</p>
               <p>The. 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. day, <hi>To the place where our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de was crouned with Thornes.</hi> Meditate in what diſtreſſe our lorde was, when the wicked ſeruants tooke him beinge ſo ſcourged, and cloathed him with a purple garment, mocked him, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15411:55"/>crowned him with a wreathed crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of thornes. what extreame paine Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus felt at his Coronation, cheifly in his braines and ſinnowes. Alſo in the impreſſion of the ſaid Crowne, how the bloode ſprange out of his veines, and how the blood of his heart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. and how the blood ranne downe about his face and neck, when he was ſtroken vpon the ſame crowne with the Reede. what greueous skorne, and torment this was altogether<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how they kneeled and mocked him.</p>
               <p>The 204. day. <hi>To the place vvhere Ieſus was shevved by Pilate, ſainge.</hi> Ecce Homo. <hi>vvhich is a vault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, In which is an arche, in the which two ſtones of white marble are ſet, vpon one Pilate ſtoode, and on the other ſtoode Ieſus.</hi> Meditate vpon the exceſſiue loue of Ieſus harte, when he ſo gently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him ſelf to be ſhewed to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beinge skant able to goe. and what ſor owe Chriſt ſuffered when Pilate ſaid. <hi>Ecce Homo.</hi> and againe the people
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15411:55"/>cringe <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olle Tolle, crucifige cum.</hi> Wher vppon Ieſus wept moſte bitterly.</p>
               <p>The 205 day <hi>To the place where Pilate led Ieſus, and inquired if he were the ſonne of god.</hi> Meditate in what piteous eſtate the noble ſoule of Ieſus was, hauinge ſo great diſhonor, deſpite, and torments done vnto him by theſe wicked men, how paciently he heard their crienges, ſainge, we haue no kinge but Ceſar. Alſo of his meeke ſilence, when Pilate asked him of whence he was &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The 206. day. <hi>To the place where our Lord receaued his iudgment and ſentence of death by Pilate. There were</hi> 80000. <hi>Iewes vvho cried for his death, as it is reuealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate what inexplicable loue was in the hart of Ieſus, which conſtranied him to be iudged of his creatures, (who were able to doe nothinge without him) and that vnto ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious and vile a death, as the death of the Croſſe, and of his ſo great patience, content, and willingnes to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15411:56"/>ſuffer al for mans redemption.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vvay of the Croſſe to wardes mount Caluarie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Moſte puiſant iudge of heauen and earth, by the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible loue, by the which thou ſufferedſt for me incomparable torments, of mockinge, whippinge, Crowning, falſe witneſſe, &amp; haſte receaued of Pilate ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to be crucified, and to die on the Croſſe moſte willingly. I beſeech thee o La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god, to geue me true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and deſpiſinge of my ſelf, and alſo perfect obedience to thee my Lorde, and to my ſuperious; and to iudge here of my ſowle, and of my doinges, to the end I may not ſeare thy ſtraight and iuſte iudgement hereafter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 207. day, <hi>To the place vvhere the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Robe was pulled of, vvhen he vvas to beare his Croſſe</hi> Meditate how humbly &amp; pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly our moſt louinge lorde ſtoode in the mideſt of the people, when they
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15411:56"/>ſpoiled him of his purple garment, and how the people ſtoode gaſinge on him to his great paine and griefe, how they put on his owne garments, that he might be the better knowen of al men. and how he caried the heauie burthen of the Croſſe for the ſinnes of al the world with exceſſiue great paines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Croſſe was.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>foote longe and</hi> 8. <hi>foot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ouerthvvart. and it vveighed,</hi> 150. <hi>pounde vvaight. From the place vvhere Chriſt vvas iudged, to the Place vvhere the Croſſe vvas laied on him, vvere</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>paces. and from the plac vvhere the Croſſe vvas laied on him to the plac vvhere he firſt fel, are</hi> 40. <hi>ſtrides, and euery ſtride conteineth tvvo comon paces, or ſix foote. And from that to the place vvhere his vvoful mother met him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvere</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>ſtrides, and three foote. There vvent vvith our Lord to mount Caluaries</hi> 15000 <hi>parſons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Moſt noble kinge, &amp; valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard beater who for the loue of me dideſt permit the heauie burthen of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15411:57"/>Croſſe, to be laied vpon thy ſhoulders (which were ful ſore with ſtripes) and there with al, al the ſinnes of the worlde, offeringe the ſame by thy death vpon the Aultar of the Croſſe, to thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, I beſeeche the healp me to cary my Croſſe, that I may wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſuſtaine the ſame, and to ſerue thee according to my vocation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 208. day, <hi>Tovvardes the mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, to the Chapel vvhere our Lady ſtoode caled</hi> Sancta Maria in plaſmo <hi>vvhere the Bleſſed virgin ſounded, Here vvas the ſeconde falinge of our Lord.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus went forwarde with his painful and heauie Croſſe, and for waight, and paine thereof, our good Lorde went almoſte double vnder it. and how the ſouldiers vſed him, cruelly ſtriking him, and reuilinge him. al which he tooke with as great patience and mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denes, as if he had bene eaſely &amp; gently entreated. and how peaceably he went betwixt two theeues, as if he had bene
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15411:57"/>the captaine, being rebuked deſpiſed and reuiled of the people as he went, vntil he went out at the gate of the citie, wherat his mother met him. and with what intollerable ſorrowe he caſt his lookes vpon hir.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The. <hi>6.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Lord god by the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of thy tender compaſſion, which thou boareſt to our infirmitie, which conſtrayned thee to carry thy Croſſe to thy great confuſion and paines, goinge betwene two theues as the Captaine of them, with thy head crowned, thy face ſwollen with blowes, disfigured with ſpittel, and al thy body wounded with effuſion of thy precious blood: and by the greate compaſſion in behouldinge thy welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued mother, when thou perceaued hir alſo ſo diſcomforted becauſe of thy dolours. I beſeech the moſte faithful mediator, that I may continualy folowe thee by loue, to the end that I
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15411:58"/>may be pertaker of thy moſte ſacred, and moſte bitter paſſion, Amen. <hi>Here ſay the</hi> Salue Regina, <hi>or thrice</hi> Aue maria. <hi>from the place where our Lady ſtoode, vnto the place where Simon Cirenct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, was compelled to carry the Croſſe of our Lorde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 209. day, <hi>In the place vvhere Simon C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reneus was compelled to carry the Croſſe of Chriſt. and here is the third falinge of our Sauiour.</hi> Meditate now how our Lorde fel for faintnes, and was not able to goe any father without healp. and how Simeon was conſtrayned againſt his wil to beare his Croſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>7</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O My Lord Ieſu Chriſt, moſte pure glaſſe of perfect patience, by thy great paine and wearines which thou enduredſt in caring thy heauie Croſſe, and falinge oft times vpon the earth, and by the loue and ardor of thy holy hart which cauſed thee to proceede. I beſeeche thee my refuge, renew the puporſe of my ſlouthful hart, wilingly
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15411:58"/>to cary after thee the ſpritual croſſe of religion, and what other ſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe thee to lay vpon me, the which of my ſelf with Simeon, I am loath, &amp; repine to cary, &amp; for want of courage, falle vnder the ſame to the end that by enflamed deſires, I may folowe thy holy ſteppes, and neuer to or faſke thy croſſe, vntil thou diſchargeſt me of the ſame at the hower of my death, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may afterward dwel with thee euerlaſtingly, amen.</p>
               <p>The 210 day, <hi>To the place where veronica preſented hir ſelf to our Lorde, There vvas the fourth time our Lorde fel. &amp; ſo to the foote of mount Caluarie, which was the fifth time.</hi> Meditate how veronica preſented to our Lorde, al fainte, extreamely wearie and ſweatinge, hir kerchir to wipe his face, and to refreſh him with al. and how our Sauiour tooke it in thankful maner, and wiped his face there with, leauinge the print of his viſage in the cloath. for a rewarde of hir great chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:15411:59"/>
               <head>The <hi>8.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Ieſu fountaine of mercie who ſo continualy proceeded, loaden with paines and dolours. &amp; gaueſt the grace to that good woman veronica to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne al weepinge among the mideſt of the ſouldiears, to ſee thee once more before thy death, &amp; to preſent to thee that cloath wher in thou dideſt leaue the image of thy face. I beſeeche thee giue me grace alwayes with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual compaſſion, for to behould thy bleſſed face ſo disfigured, that ſo thy Diuine hart may be printed in my harte, that it be neuer defiled with ſinne and that thy face may alwaies ſhew mercie to me <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The cloth of</hi> Veronica <hi>is at Rome, in Saint Peters Church, and is often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wed in the holy vveeke, and the Aſcention day and on the next Sonday after</hi> Saint Anthonies <hi>Feaſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 211. day, <hi>To the place where Ieſus turned to the vvomen that be vvailed him,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15411:59"/>here vvas the ſixte faling. Ieſus behelde the mounte Caluerie vvith verie greate heuines and ſadnes, vvhere he vvas to ende his daies in tormentes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate how Ieſus turned to the women that wepte after him, and ſaid vnto them, yee daughters of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, weepe not forme, but wepe for your ſelues and for your Children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Moſt meeke lambe, by the great violence thou ſufferedſt of thoſe feirce and cruell Lions, who haſtned to traile and drawe thee to be crucified, and to ſhede thy precious bloode, &amp; who mercifully looked with thy eie of compaſſion vpon the women that lamented, and knewe not the miſterie of thy paſſion to be for the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mankinde, and for the ſinnes of the worlde. I beſeche thee to ſoften my ſtony harte, that I may ſhed a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares in contemplation of thy bitter paſſion, which my iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15411:60"/>were the cauſe of and that I may eſcape the euerlaſting torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. <hi>Amen.</hi> The 112. day, <hi>Before the doore of the temple of the holie ſepulcre, vvich is neare to the foote of mounte Caluarie, neare the ſtone vvhere our Lord fell the laſt time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate with what ardour of loue our Lorde behelde the great height of mounte Caluarie, and how he wente vp labouring, and bearing his heauie Croſſe, and heare fel once more, which was the 7. time, and laye there as if he had no life in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>10</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Bottomles deapth of loue, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by the feruour of this loue, where with thou ſo much deſiredeſt the ſaluation of mankinde and thereby waſt drawen vp the high hill of Caluarie, to which thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſt with ſo manie blodie ſteppes, to offer thy ſelfe to thy father, on the painful Aulter of the Croſſe in ſatisfaction of our offences, and for faintnes dideſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15411:60"/>fale on thy face at the foote of the hill vpon a harde ſtone, lieng as if thou hadeſt no life in thee. I beſech thee who arte readie to take mercie on all ſinners who doe conuerte and repente and pardoneſt all ſuch as are trulie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite. I beſech thee to pardon me all my enormious offences, vvith the vvhich I haue bene ouerthrowne, and houlde me vp vvith thy holy feare, that I may alwaies ſtand firme in the ſtate of grace. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heare thou ſhalt enter the Temple of the holie ſepulcre, where thou ſhalt ſay the Pſalme. <hi>Letatus ſum in his. &amp;c. Anthiph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na terribilis eſt io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us iſte, vere non eſt hic, &amp;t. verſ. Domum tuam Domine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et ſanctitudo Reſp in longitudine dierum.</hi> or ſay 3. <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aue maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>11.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Lord who vouchſafed to ſende thy deare and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Sonne, to be Crucified, anointed, and buried, and riſing to appeare to <hi>Marie Magl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lene,</hi> I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15411:61"/>beſeche thee giue me thy grace in this life, and in the life to come euerlaſting glorie <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novve you are to goe to the Quiere of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vvhere the Gaurdaine of the friers doth leade the Pilgrimes to viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te al the holy places. Deſire</hi> S. Francis, <hi>and the reſt of this holie companie, that thy vvill praie for thee, and obtaine for thee a ſinguler grace, of compunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thy ſinns, and compaſſion of the paines of thy Sauiour, and to haue a moſt ardent lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ovvardes him. And thou muſt haue a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Candel in thy hande and ſay the Himme</hi> Chriſte qui lux es et dies. Antiph O Crux ſpes Vnica &amp;t. <hi>The littanies. &amp;</hi> Salue Regina. <hi>In the Cloiſter is a Chappell vvhere our Lorde did ſit on the ſtone and is caled the priſon of our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 123. day, <hi>At the Stone vvhere on our Lord did ſitt.</hi> Meditate how theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful Iewes did with greate vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence pul of the cloathes ouer our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours heade which did ſtick to his body, where by al his woundes began
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15411:61"/>to bleede a freſhe, and how he ſtóode alſo in a pitiful maner, naked before al the people alſo how hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly he behaued him ſelf, when he was ſet vpon the ſtone betwixt the two theeues, ful of ſorrowe, attending whilſt the croſſe was made readie, and there they gaue him vineger mingled with gaule to drinke, and to the theeues good wine. conſider alſo the greueous wounde he had on his ſhowlder with carieng the heauie Croſſe, and pray thy Lorde, that by the deapth and paine of that wounde, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will heale thee of al thy wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. <hi>There vvere rounde hoales about the ſtoe through vvhich his ſeete went.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>11.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Sweete Sauiour Ieſus, my loue and hartes deſier, who vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedſt to be ſpoiled of thy garmentes with ſpite and villanie, to thy great paine and ſhame, and to ſee thoſe vile men caſte lottes for thy garments, and deuide them, ſettinge thee vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtone
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15411:62"/>betwixt two theeues, and deridinge thee. Let it pleaſe thee to vncloath me from, al ſingular affection, and ſelf loue, and that it wold pleaſe thee to appearel me, with the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy holy loue, by which thou haſte ſo mercifully, by thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, bound me vnto thee, that ſo at the hower of my death, I may with ful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence flie in to thy holy armes <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This garment is yet at Treuirs, and many other Reliques. as the Speare vvhich opened his ſacred ſide. and one of the three Nailes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 214. day, <hi>At the place vvhere our Lord was nailed to the Croſſe,</hi> Meditate how theſe vile and cruel wretches did leade our Sauiour, from the aforeſaid ſtone to the Croſſe, where they threwe him viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his back, on the hard Croſſe that it hurt him very ſore, and ſhooke al the veines of his holy harte: which he tooke in good parte, with patience, for the loue which he had of the ſaluation of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde: &amp; how mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15411:62"/>he ſpread his armes a broade of his owne accorde, to be nailed with thoſe boiſterous nailes of Iron. Alſo how al his body was extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſtretched with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des that it cracked, &amp; that the veines &amp; ſinewes did breake a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hed like a ſtringe on a Bowe. and with what patience he ſuffered the ſame: and how they troade on him, &amp; with their feete ſpurned, and thruſt his head where they would haue it lye, takinge greate pleaſure in their cruelty and tormentinge of him: Alſo how they ſtrooke on his head &amp; ſides with their hammers, in ſomuch that the blood did iſſue forth of his noſe and mouth. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber alſo the great ſorowe his bleſſed mother had when ſhe heard the blowes of the hammers, and What countenance ſhe had ſeing the body of hir deere ſonne al bloody, and in ſo piteous a plight. <hi>The Iewes giue him</hi> 50. <hi>blovves vvith hammers vvhen they faſtened him vpon the Croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:15411:63"/>
               <head>The <hi>13.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Sweete Ieſus by al the paines and anguiſhes thou ſufferedſt when thou waſt ſtretched on the Croſſe, with great courage and patience for me mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable catife, beinge moſte cruely faſtned on the ſame geue me grace I beſeech thee to vſe wel al the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of my body in thy holy ſeruice, and that when the bitternes and panges of death ſhal ſtretch al my members, I may then remember thy greueous pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and dolours, and with thee offer my ſelf in Sacrifice, and patiently to endure al which thy holy pleaſure ſhal be to ſend me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At an Aultar in the quier, is a place vvhere the vvicked played at dice for Chriſtes gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, at which place our bleſſed Lady and Magdalen did greatly ſorrow. On the left hand it is where the Iewes prepared the vinegar and gaule. In a Chappel vnder the ground is the place vvhere ſainte Helin was wont to pray, and vvhere the died, and vvas firſt buried, but
<pb n="811" facs="tcp:15411:63"/>after vvas tranſlated to venice. Yet deeper is the place vvhere S. Helin found the three Croſſes, and three nayles, and the Crowne of Thornes. Aſcendinge on another Aultar thou shalt finde vnder the ſame a shorte Piller, vvhere on our Lord d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſit vvhen the crovvne of Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vvas put on his head now you aſcende the mounte of Caluarie vvhich is a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te Rocke there is afaire Church or Chappell vvhich is all gilded vvith goulde and azur, and is paued vvith marble. On the one ſide there is the place vvhere our lord vvas hanged on the croſſe into this place fevve people doe enter. By the doore there is the hoale of the holie Croſse all open tvvo foote deepe, and a ſpace brode, into vvhich you may put your arme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 215 day. To contemplate howe our Lord Ieſus was lifted from the grounde, and carried to be ſet betwene tow theeues to his greater ſhame, and to ſuffer moſte bitter death for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankinde. Meditate of the exceſſiue loue which our Sauiour Ieſus had of the health and ſaluation
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15411:64"/>of mankinde, which was kindled in his diuine harte like a burning fire, which cauſed him ſo patiently to be lifted vp, ſhaked, and let fale vpon the grounde, with vnſpeakeable paine to all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie members, which ſtroke vnto the hatre of his dolorous mother. The which fale he ſuſteined that the diuine iuſtice ſhould not eternally condemne the poore ſinner, at euerie time hee ſhoulde fale into deadly ſinne. And how he was lifted vp &amp; ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te betwixt two theues? and how he was annoyed with the ſtincke &amp; ſauour of the dead bodies which were on mounte Calua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p>The 216. day, meditate with what greate patience our Lord endured to be crucified, ſtretched, nailed, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and diſhonored as well in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, as in his humanitie, by the high Preiſts, Scribes, Phariſes, and Elders, who contrarie to the lawe followed after for this effecte, vvhich was more
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15411:64"/>tormente vnto him then any of his other paines, wherevpon with greate humilitie, he beganne to pray for his enimies, (the 1. worde) <hi>My father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue them they knovve not vvhat they doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 217. day meditate in the ſame place, with how greate pacience our Lorde Ieſus endured in thoſe intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the ſpace of three hours hanging on the Croſſe, hauing not the meanes to moue any one of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, where one might eaſealy number euerie bone, and ſee his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ines and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewes. Of the blaſphemie of one of the theeues, and of the repentance of the good theefe. And of the words of Ieſus to him (the 2. worde) <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> day thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>halt be vvith me in Paradice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>8 day, meditate this day of the vnſpeakeable ſorrowe which our lords broken harte did feele, vvhen he did behoulde his heuie and diſcomforted Mother by him, to whome hee ſpake in this manner. (The 3. vvorde) <hi>VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15411:65"/>behoulde thy Sonne.</hi> And after to S. Iohn. <hi>Behoulde thy mother.</hi> Where at they both helde there peace, not being able to ſpeake for ſorrowe and teares.</p>
               <p>The 219. day meditate in vvhat great diſtreſſe the body of our Lord did hang ſeeking vvith intollerabe paines, to turne, or vvinde himſelfe vpon the Croſſe, thinking to finde ſome more eaſe, and ſo vveeping bloodie teares, cried to his father vvith a high voice, (the 4 worde) <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> god my god vvhie haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> thy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ſonne into the handes of ſinners. and how darkenes came ouer all the whole earth from the ſixt houre to the ninth houre, and the ſunne alſo loſt his light.</p>
               <p>The 220. day meditate vvhat extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e pouertie our lorde endured vpon the Croſſe, vvhen all his naturall humors were ſpent and run out, and in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding drieth cried out (the 5, worde) <hi>I thirſte.</hi> And how he coulde not gette ſo much as a litle coulde vvater. How
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15411:65"/>one of the iniuſte &amp; vvicked miniſters filled a ſponge vvith vineger, mingled with gale, &amp; put it to the mouth of Ieſus, but when he taſted it he would not drinke it. To the ende that we ſhoulde not taſte of the cup of death euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>The 221. day Meditate how our Lord endured peaceably, and patiently al the paines and torments of the Croſſe by which meanes he ſatisfied and paid to god his father the det for our ſinnes: which Ieſus conſideringe from pointe to pointe therof, and findinge al to be fulfilled which the Scriptures and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies had fore tould of him, he cried (the 6. word) <hi>It is finished.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 222. day, Meditate how our Lord Ieſus prepated him ſelf to die, and of the great patience he had when death was now come in to his woundes, in to his bones, and began to aſſault his ſacred hart. at the firſt aſſault heauen and earth trembled. At the ſecond, the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15411:66"/>ſtones and Rockes did cleaue a ſonder and the graues of the dead did open. At the third aſſault which was moſte feirce, thorough loue, he willingely yealded his hart to be tranſperced to death, and therfore cried (the 7. word) <hi>In to thy handes o Lord I comend my ſpirite,</hi> and bowinge downe his head he gaue vp the ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his death al the vvorld vvas moued. the earth trembled: the ſtones cloaue in peices. the Sepulchers opened. the veile of the Temple rent in tvvo. The Centurion ſeing al theſe mirackles, and that he died vveepinge he ſaid, verely this man vvas the ſonne of god and the people aſtonied at al they ſaw and heard, returned to their ovvne houſes knockinge their breaſtes. The mount of Caluarie alſo cleft as it is novv ſeene, four foote from the boale vvhere in the croſſe vvas put, at the left ſide tovvardes the euil theefe, it is ſo longe that a man may lie here in, and</hi> 18, <hi>foote deepe as is thought. In he cleaunige of the Rocke the Croſſe of the eui be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe vvent farther of. Our Sauiour did ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15411:66"/>on the croſſe vvith his face tovvardes the vveſt. he vvas then</hi> 33. <hi>yeares old</hi> 3. <hi>monethes, and</hi> 9. <hi>dayes. There vvas founde therby a vvritinge in greeke letters ſainge.</hi> Illic deus rex noſter ante ſaecula operatus eſt ſalutem in medio terrae.</p>
               <p>The 223 day. Meditate how the moſte noble ſoule of our Sauiour left his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred body hanginge on the croſſe in moſte miſerable and doleful plight, when it departed forth in ſo great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, his cheekes were riueled, his noſe ſharpe, his eies and ſweete mouth were halfe open, his head inclined and hanging downe vpon his breaſte, his ſides vvere very rawe, and thinne, and ſo as euery bone might be eaſely toulde, his belly was ſuncke inward to his back, his legges were turned to one ſide, and his feete to a nother, al his whole body was ful of woundes, and of colour red, black &amp; blue that it was pittie to ſee it. If it be thus o Lord in thy body which was conceiued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:15411:67"/>our ſinne, borne of a virgin, moſte pure and innocent in al thy life, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with thy diuinitie. what ought I miſerable ſinner to haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, if thy great mercie o Lord had not preuented me. and with thy bitter paines and torments thou hadeſt not redeemed me.</p>
               <p>The 224. day, meditate of the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ſorrow of the bleſſed mother of god, ſeinge hir ſweete and wel beloued ſome hanging dead on the Croſſe, and what abundance of teares ſhe ſhed, with S. Iohn, and other women of his freindes. and what feare they were in when as the officers came &amp; brake the leggs of both the theeues that ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Ieſus that they might die the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner. And how that (ſeing Ieſus was dead) one of the ſouldiers ſtroke our. Lorde to the harte with a ſpeare, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iſſued out bloode and water, for our redemption, and the remiſſion of our ſinnes. The which thruſt of the ſpeare
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15411:67"/>peirced the hart of our bleſſed Ladie alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>13.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Moſt mightie conquerour of all our enimies, by the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible loue and paine which thou ſufferedſt being ſtreched like a ſtringe vpon the Croſse, as well inwardly as outwardly, thy veines and ſinnewes being broken there withall that thy precious bloode iſſued forth like foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taines of water. And by all the mocks blaſphemies &amp; iniuries thou then did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſuffer, when in ſo great torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou yealdeſt vp thy bleſſed ſoule vnto thy heauenly father in full ſatiſfaction for all our ſinnes. I beſeche thee geue me grace to perſeuer in true pennance &amp; to die to the worlde and heare to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for mine offences. O Lorde hould me faſt by thoſe three nailes of my chriſtian profeſſion, that is to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the worlde the fleſhe &amp; the diuell. As alſo by theſe 3. nailes of Religion, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15411:68"/>Chaſtitie, and obedience, that I neuer fal from thy loue into any ſinne or greueous temptation and that I may at the hower of my death with ful confidence ſay. <hi>In to thy handes o Lorde I commende my ſpirite.</hi> &amp; ſo heare thy voice ful of mercie with the good theefe ſainge. <hi>This day thou stalt be with me in Paradiſe,</hi> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly glorie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 225. day. <hi>To a Chappel on mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarie, vvhere our Lady and S. Iohn ſtoode, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lord ſpoke to them on the croſse. Therby is an Aultar vvhere Abraham made ſacrifice to our lord. Before this Aulter lieth buried S. Godfrie of Bullein, Baldwine his brother, and many chriſtian kinges of Hieruſalem. As you goe to the doore is a black ſtone hauinge.</hi> 7. <hi>lampes hanging ouer it, vvhich is the place where our Lady ſat, vvhen Ieſus vvas taken from the Croſse and laied in hir lappe, as she vvith teares requeſted. this is almoste the halfe vvay betwixt the Croſſe and the Sepulcher The woundes our Sauiour receaued in his body vvere.</hi> 6666. <hi>or as ſome other ſay,</hi> 5475.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:15411:68"/>
Meditate how the noble man Ioſeph of Arimathia and Nichodemus came to take downe the body of our lord from the croſſe with maruelous great reuerence and deuotion, both to the body, to the croſſe, and to his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother. which ſhe receaued with maruelous and incredible doloure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The. <hi>14.</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Moſte merciful redeemer, by the great ſorrowe of thy deere mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when thy moſte ſacred body was taken from the Croſſe and laid in hir armes, in a faire cloath, which ſhe waſhed with many teares. I beſeeche thee by the ſame ſorrowe and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſoften my drye, hard, and ſtony hart, beinge a moſte wretched and vile ſinner, that I may inceſſantly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my ſinnes and wickednes, and with compaſſion and thankfulnes, to bewaile thy bitter death and paſſion, and at my death, to receaue deuoutly and worthely thy holy body &amp; blood,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15411:69"/>and ſo with a pure conſcience to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vnited vnto thee. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note that the diſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e betwixt the Croſte, and the Sepulcher, is</hi> 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>foote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. 226. day, <hi>Towardes the place of the Sepulcher which is in the midel of the body of the Temple, vvich Temple is rounde vvith in, and vaulted aboute hauinge</hi> 73. <hi>Pillers, euery one beinge</hi> 30. <hi>foote highe. vvon the Sepulcher is a great rounde houle, as large and wide as is the Caue of the Sepulcher, ſo as it is open fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes the element. the entrie to the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is But.</hi> 3. <hi>foote high, and the colour of it vvithin is grey. It is.</hi> 7. <hi>foote longe, and</hi> 6. <hi>foote vvide, and.</hi> 9. <hi>foote and a halfe highe. And on the right ſide towards the North, is the holy Sepulcher of our lorde, and eight handfulls highe from the grounde, is a stone as big as a mans head of the Sepulcher, faſtned in the vval, which Pilgrimes doe kiſse. In this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nackle is no vvindowes, but only la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes burninge. there is a lampe hanginge before the holy Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, but on good friday it goeth out of it ſelf, and lighteth of the one accorde on the holy
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15411:69"/>night of Easter at the hower our lorde did riſe from death. Alſo at the Sepulcher is a faire Tombe of marble, vvhich is an Aultar, very ſtreight, where there can enter but three or fouer perſons. there burne.</hi> 18. <hi>lampes, and there is Maſſe ſaid before the knightes of the Sepulcher, vvhich are kinghted in the ſame place. Noble men and gentelmen are here made kinghtes, hauing a girdel of goulde and a gylte ſvvorde put a bout them, and gylte Spurres ò their heeles. and enclininge in prayer before the Sepulcher, take an oath, &amp; are doubed kinghts by the gardein of the Friers, of vvhom he recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</hi> 3. <hi>blowes in the neck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate how the night beinge come, the honorable frendes vvho tooke Ieſus downe, deſiered the mother of our Lord, that it would now pleaſe hir to permit them to bury his dead body; and how Ioſeph and Nichode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus wrapped Ieſus in a cleane Sindon or cloath, with mirrhe, Aloes, and ſweete ſpices, and rowled a great ſtone to the mouth of the Sepulcher, when
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15411:70"/>they had laied Ieſus there in, in the ſight of his doleful mother, who wept bitterly, with other his frendes: and ſo they al departed home becauſe of the night in great heauines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The <hi>15</hi> Station.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Lorde, and Sauiour of mankinde, whom it hath pleaſed to endure ſo much for my loue, wretch that I am, I beinge the cauſe of thy death and paſſion. I beſeeche thee by the merites of thy precious death, which thou haſt endured with ſo great loue for me, that thou wilt geue life to my ſoule, and pardon al my ſinnes, and paines due for them, both in this life and at my death, and that I may euery day learne to die wel, to the end I may liue with thee euerlaſtingly <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 227. day, Meditate how our Lord Ieſus did ariſe by his owne proper force and verru the third day out of the cloſed Sepulcher victoriouſly, like
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15411:70"/>a noble &amp; valiant Champian. and firſt appeared to his deare mother, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compained with a multitude of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: whoe ioyed with vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy and gladnes, and the Angels ſounge <hi>Regina caeli letare. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before the highe Aultar in the quiere is the place vvhere our Lady vvas vvhen our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red to hiron Eaſter day. Before t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e great Aultar is a fair marble ſtone, vvhere on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lorde ſtoode wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n he appeared to our Ladie And this is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtone vpon vvhich S. Helen proued the; Croſſes by layinge a dead body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them On th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> left hand there is an Aultar on vvhich the holy Croſſe remayned a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge time after</hi> S Helen <hi>found it. on the right hand of the quiare is a longe, and great peece of the Piller, vvhere vnto our Lorde vvas bounde vvhen he was whipped. VVhere he receaued.</hi> 624 <hi>ſtripes. Nere there vnto are</hi> 4. <hi>Pillers vvhich continualy ſvveate vvater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. day Meditate how our Lord appeared to Mary Magdalen in likenes of a Gardner, when ſhe ſat weepinge
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15411:71"/>at the Sepulcher, and how ſweetly he comforted hir, commandinge hir to declare his Reſurrection, to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and to S. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Betvvene the Sepulcher of our Lorde and the quiare of our Ladie, ar tvvo Tombes, which are tvvo marble ſtones vpon the which our Lorde on the one appeared like a Gardner and Mary Magdalen ſatt on the other. Before the Church of the holy Sepulcher tovvardes the South is a great Hoſpital of S. Iohn Baptiſte, vvhere was Zacharies houſe S. Iohn Baptiſts father. Bethanie lieth tovvards the North tvvo miles from Hieruſalem before the mount of Oliuet nere Bethpage. At the end of Bethanie is the Place vvhere Martha met our Lord and toulde him that hir brother Lazarus vvas dead. There is alſo shevved the place vvhere Ieſus went to lodge. Nere that is a Caſtel of Magdalen. Nere Hieruſalem is the Caſtle vvhere Lazarus dwelt, &amp; the Sepulcher whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Ieſus raiſed him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is the houſe of Simeon the eper, where Mary Magdalen anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15411:71"/>the feete of our Lorde. Returninge to Hieruſalem you paſſe by the Figtree which our Lorde curſed and it withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red incontinently.</p>
               <p>The 229 day. Meditate how Ieſus after his Reſurrection appeared to the three women in the way, whom he ſaluted louingly ſaing <hi>Auete</hi> where they caſt them ſelues proſtrate on the earth, and kiſſed his feete.</p>
               <p>The 230. day <hi>At the Caue vvhere. S Peter vvept bitterly for that he had denied his maſter.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus appeared to Saint Peter who was extreame ful of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe for that he had denied his maſter &amp; how Ieſus lifted him vp louingly &amp; pardoned his offence. likewiſe how he comforted S. Iames caled the brother of our Lorde, becauſe of the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance he had with our Lorde, who had vowed he wold neither eate nor, drinke, vntil he had ſene our Lord to be riſen. likewiſe he comforted Ioſeph of Arimathia, and Nichodemus.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:15411:72"/>
The 21. day, meditate how Ieſus ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed himſelfe like a pilgrime to the two diſciples going to Emaus, howe they knewe him by breaking of bread, and how they returned to ſeruſalem, and ſhewed to the diſciples that our Lord was riſen.</p>
               <p>The 233. day, meditate how Ieſus that Eaſter day at night, the doores being ſhut, ſtode amonge his diſciples, ſaing, <hi>Pax vobis</hi> and ſhewed them that he was cruely riſen from death</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>32, day, meditate how Ieſus. 8. daies after his reſurrection appeared againe the doores being ſhutt, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed his diſciples his woundes, &amp; ſaied to <hi>Thomas</hi> put thy finger into my woundes, and thy handes into my ſide and be not incredulous but beleuing. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid my Lorde and my God. and Chriſt to him. Becauſe thou haſt ſeene me thou beleueſt, but bleſſed be they vvhich beleeue and ſee not.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="voyage">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:15411:72"/>
            <head>THE VOYAGE OF BETHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM LYING TOWARDES THE South a great mile of Almaine from Hieruſalem, a faier way full of Vines.</head>
            <p>OVt of the gate of Hieruſalem is the houſe of iuſt <hi>Simeon.</hi> A litle farther is the place vvhere the <hi>3</hi> Kinges did ſee the ſtarre, vvhich appeared in the Eaſte. <hi>Betheſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is a litle tovvne, long, and ſtraight, compaſſed vvith great dit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes, ſcituated vpon a litle mountaine neare the valley of Hebyon, and is extended from Eaſte to weſte there is the faireſt Church of the holie lande. with <hi>48.</hi> Pillers of marble adorned with hiſtories from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of the worlde, to the natiuitie of Chriſt, couered vvith marble of diuers coullours, and the wales ſeeled with allablaſter and marble <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</hi> foote longe and broade. There are <hi>12.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeous Friers.</p>
            <p>The 234 day, meditate how Ieſus ſhewed himſelfe neare the ſea of Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias to his diſciples who were gone to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15411:73"/>fiſhe with S. Peter, and had caught no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing al the night, and when the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning came our Lorde appeared vnto them ſtanding on the bancke, and aſked them ſome thing to eate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to caſte their netts on the right ſide of the baote where they caught 153. great fiſhes. And Ieſus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde aſked S. <hi>Peter</hi> three times if he loued him, commanding him to to feede his lambes and ſheepe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVithin the Cloiſter of the friers dovvne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ground is the ſepulere of</hi> S. Hierome. <hi>and there ie</hi> S. Euſebius <hi>Sepulchre on the other ſide. There is the place vvhere</hi> S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome <hi>tranſlated the Bible out of Hebrue into latin. Tovvardes the South is an Aulter vvhere our lorde vvas circumciſed. on the north is an Aulter where the three kinges made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> readie to make their offeringe. Goirge lower is a Chappel ioyninge to the Rock, wher Ieſus vvas borne in this Chapel is a faire ſtene like a Starre with fiue or ſix beames vvhereon our Lady kenceled and adored hir ſonne when he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15411:73"/>vvas newly borne, ouer this ſtone is an Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. Three ſteppes lower is the manger vvhere our lord vvas laid, being of marble, vnderſet vvith tvvo pillers, and a foote highe. ſay here thy Beades Pray here to Christe new borne in the manger t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> graunt thee grace to be new borne in him, and that as he vvas pertaker of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, ſo he vvil make vs partakrr of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie. Behinde this Chappel is a hoale, vvhere the Starre did lead the</hi> 3 <hi>kinges, and abide there a while<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> retorninge to the Chapel of Saint Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin in this Church, there is a place where ſome of the Innocent children were caſt. The nomber of the children vvhich Herod ſlevve, were CXLiiij thouſand Goinge from Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelem Eaſtward about halfe amile is the place vvhere the virgin Marie, vvent vvith Ieſus and Ioſeph when she should flie into Egipt thence yee goe into a pleſant valley where the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles appeared eo the Sheppards, and tould them tidinges of the birth of our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="voyages">
               <head>The voiages towardes the mountaines of Iudea</head>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:15411:74"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeſe mountaines are ten miles north from Bethelem, and the way very crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. there Zacharie dwelt and Elizabeth, and there is yet the howſe vvhere our Lady and Elizabeth, met and greeted ſo louingly there is alſo a fountaine where our Lady fetched vvater vvhilſt she remained there. Aboute a shoote fartheris Zacharies houſe vvhere Saint Iohn Baptiſte vvas borne. A litel thence is a Church vvhere Saint Iohn vvas circumciſed, &amp; there is the Caue where Saint Iohn was kept priſoner by Herod. Betwene Emaus, &amp; Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem you come to a Church caled</hi> Ad Saincta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Crucem, <hi>vvhere is a Cloiſter of Greeke mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes of S. Benetts ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. Goinge to Hieruſalem ſay the pſalme</hi> Lauda Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m. &amp;c <hi>vſe ſome prayers in al the holy places, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the conneniencie of thinges there done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. 235. day. <hi>At the mount Oliuet where is a Chappel.</hi> Meditate how Ieſus often filled the hartes of his Diſciples with ioy, eſpecially at his Aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion, his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his diſciples, and frendes both men and women, accompained with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15411:74"/>infinite nombers of Angels, and Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, and of fathers from limbo, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended with great glorie.</p>
               <p>The 36 day, <hi>To the mount of Sion, vvhere i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Chappel aſcending behinde the highe Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, vvhere the holy Ghoste came downe vpon the Apostles.</hi> Meditate how the father and the Sonne ſent the holie Ghoſte vnto the Apoſtles in the ſimilitude of fierie tounges, and reſted vpon each of them, and were there by confirmed in in faith ſo that they preached bouldly thorough out al the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now prepare thy ſelf to retorne againe to thy home, comending thy ſelf both body and ſovvle to almightie god, and goe novv once more to the holy Sepulcher to take thy laſte leaue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The. 337. day.</hi> At the Sepulcher, and the mount of Caluary ſay here the Prayer folwinge.</head>
               <p>O My lord god, and Sauiour Ieſus, I yeald thee humble thankes for my creation and redemption in this
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15411:75"/>place, and haſt by thy vocation and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration caled me and brought me to the vnderſtandinge and knowledge of thee and hauinge ſo patiently atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded me, fallinge ſo often in to many ſinnes, and deliuered me from infinite periles, and afflictions, which I haue iuſtlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. I giue thee thankes for thy gifts and graces begune in me, and I beſech thee o lorde to reforme me, and directe my waies, that I may in the ende come to thy euerlaſting glorie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>An aduertiſment.</head>
               <p>AL the good and deuout Pilgrims hauing viſited the holy places, in their returning home looke ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times backe againe. ſo likewiſe the ſpitituall Pilgrime may well looke backe vnto the holie places, &amp; eſpecially he ought to conſider our Sauiour hanginge on the croſſe, to the ende that the bitter death of thy Sauiour goe not out of thy harte.</p>
               <p>Firſt conſider how the ſoule of our
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15411:75"/>Sauiour hanging on the Croſſe regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the ſinnes, both mortall and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, of all the worlde, for which he ſighed moſt bitterlie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doe thou knock on thy breaſt and ſigh for thy ſinnes, for which the Sonn of God hath ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt biterlie.</p>
               <p>The 2, 8 day, <hi>From Hieruſalem to Rama.</hi> Secondly meditate looking backe to the holie places, making thy praier, &amp; thinke what ſorrow &amp; greife the hart of thy lorde-Ieſus ſufferred, when hee thought and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nſiderd what a ſmale nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſhould participare of the fruits of his paſſion, the which he ſo willing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he ſufferred; and with ſuch exceſſiue, loue, as that he woulde rather ſufferre for euerie man once againe, then that anie through this defaulte ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine loſte, ſuch was his ardent loue to the ingrateful and harde hartes of outs.</p>
               <p>The 2, 9 <hi>To Iapha.</hi> Thirdelie meditate of the great bitternes which the ſoule of Chriſt endured on the Croſſe when
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15411:76"/>he conſidered that religious perſons &amp; clarkes retired from the worlde, would yeat ſoile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with carnal works for which he trembled and weepte on the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>The 340 day, <hi>In the oulde ſellers of</hi> Iapha. <hi>vvhere the Pilgrimes lodge.</hi> Fourthlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the biternes of the ſoule of Chriſt when he conſidered that the eſtate of mariage woulde be defiled with foule and execrable ſinnes, whereby ſo great a multitude of maried people ſhoulde be damned.</p>
               <p>The 341. day, fiftly meditate vvhat ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the ſoule of Ieſus Chriſt was in on the Croſſe, to thinke how the ſtate of virginitie ſhoulde be defiled, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny virgins looſing the crowne of their virginities, by conſenting to foule and filthy thoughts and deeds, for which he ſighed piteouſly.</p>
               <p>The 342 day, ſixtly conſider the great ſorrowe of the harte of our Sauiour Chriſt, to thinke vpon the wonderfull
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15411:76"/>vnthankefulnes of man to his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, for al the benifites, and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his onelie ſonne beſtowed on v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with ſo greate loue.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.3 day, <hi>From Iapha to the ship of Saint Peter,</hi> recommending thee to S. Fraucis and to al his order, recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thee to the holie Trinitie. Geue thankes to our Lorde who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted thee to theſe holie places, and that he wil be our guide and conducte vs to his heauenly kingdome. when the ſhippe beginneth to goe ſay <hi>Tedeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Seaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlhie meditate the bitter ſorrow of the ſoule of our Sauiour, conſidering that ſo manie Chriſtians ſhoulde be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for there wicked life, and then he cried. <hi>My god, my god vvhie haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 344. meditate in what greife the ſoule of Ieſus was in to conſider what nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of people ſhould remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the chriſtian faith, and therefore ſhoulde neuer ſee the face of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:15411:77"/>
The 345. day, meditate how the moſt noble ſoule of Ieſus was exceding ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, when he did conſider that the grace of God ſhoulde be of ſo litle eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation with manie, or altogether cleane reiected.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>46. day, meditate of the ſadnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoule of Ieſus when he did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and know, that yet ſo many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould goe back and fal from the vnion of holy church, and geue them ſelues to diuers ſectes.</p>
               <p>The 147. day, Meditate of the ſadnes of the ſowle of Ieſus, when he conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how often the ſonne of god ſhould be crucified againe, by the occaſion of ſinners and vnbeleuinge people.</p>
               <p>The 248. day, Meditate of the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aowe of the ſowle of Chriſt vpon the Croſſe, when he perceiued ſo many people ſhould take a iuſte cauſe of a mendment of life in hand, but not perſeuer in the ſame.</p>
               <p>The 249, day, <hi>Approachinge to Cypres
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15411:77"/>vvhich co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth, about it ſeauen Italian myles.</hi> Meditate of the great ſorowe of the ſowle of Ieſus, when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered the ſowle of man created to the ſimilitude of god ſhould be defiled with ſinne.</p>
               <p>The 250. day, <hi>In Cypres vvhere Lazarus lined before he went to Marſelles.</hi> Meditate on the bitter ſorow the ſowle of Ieſus ſuffered, when he conſidered that the nature of man who was created to no other end but to deſier heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things, would applie it ſelf ſo much to baſe and earthly thinges, and ſo defile and ſpot it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The 251. day, <hi>Vpon the mountaine of the Croſſe in Cypres.</hi> Meditate of the great ſorowe the ſowle of Ieſus had on the Croſſe, when he did ſee ſo fair an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of holy Religion ſhould be ouerthrowen, by gluttony, dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and fleaſhly ſinnes.</p>
               <p>The 252. day, Meditate of the moſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bitter ſorrowe of Ieſus when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eced t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at charitie, the ſeruice of god
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15411:78"/>and his ſeruice, would decay, war colde, and be almoſt aboliſhed, in al eſtates.</p>
               <p>The 253. day, Meditate of the ſorowe of Ieſus, when he ſaw the great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that was to come vpon ſinners, at the hower of their death, for their ingratitude.</p>
               <p>The 254. day, Meditate of the ſorowe of Ieſus, when he did conſider the great ſorowe, and il wil of ſinners, when they ſhould be deliuered to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual damnation.</p>
               <p>The 255. day Meditate of the great ſorowe of Ieſus, when he conſidered that the habitation of the holy ghoſte, which is the ſoule of man, ſhould be in many the habitation of the deuil.</p>
               <p>The 256 day Meditate of the ſorowe of Ieſus when he did conſider that one man would by perſwaſion and exſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of ſinne, leade another to damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on.</p>
               <p>The 257. day, Meditate of the ſorowe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15411:78"/>of Ieſus when he did conſider how the deuil would hinder ſo many noble creatures, to come againe to their firſt beginninge.</p>
               <p>The 258 day, Meditate of the great ſorowe of Ieſus when he did conſider that ſo many huminie creatures woulde receiue the Bleſſed Each triſt vow orthely, which was one of the greaſt ſorowes his ſowle ſuffered on the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>The 259. day, Meditate of the great ſorowe of Ieſus when he did conſider that ſo many creatures ſhould with mouth confeſſe that they knewe god, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad in their workes denie him.</p>
               <p>The 260 day, Meditate of the ſorowe of Ieſus when he conſidered ſo many humane creatures, would cary vnder a Religious habit a ſleathly heart.</p>
               <p>The 261 day, Meditate on the ſorowe of Ieſus ſoule, conſidering how ſmale regarde ſhould be made, of the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, cruel paines, and torments
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15411:79"/>which he ſuffered for vs.</p>
               <p>The 262 day, <hi>At Baffo vvhere the</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>persdor lie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the vvorkes paines, and pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtie of Ieſus chaunged in to glorie</hi> Meditate how the eternal ſonne of god after al his paines and tribulations, is receiued of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very ioyfully, vith great gladnes of al the Angelical Spirites.</p>
               <p>The 263. day, Meditate with what triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantioy, not only the three kinges, but alſo al the heauenly powers, doe make inceſſant ioyes, offeringe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen without ceaſinge, the goulde of loue and charitie, the Francumſence of iubilation and thank ſgeucinge, and the mirthe of honor and reuerence, with moſte ſweete admiration.</p>
               <p>The 264. day, Meditate how ſweetely the moſte noble humanity of Chriſt is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>alted and prayſed in heauen, for his circumciſion, when his firſt blood was ſhed on earth, and he was named Ieſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:15411:79"/>
The 265, day, Meditate of the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial citie of his father ful of al ioye and ſweetnes, where our Lord Ieſus ſitteth in al glorie, al ſorowe &amp; greife beinge far from him.</p>
               <p>The 266 day, Thinke how the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Sauiour is like a ſweete hearbour or garden to them that are loaden with the Croſſe of Pennance temptation, and tribulation, in the which ſingular comfort is to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</p>
               <p>The 267. day, Meditate how amiable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the heauenly father embraceth his moſte deare ſonne, who hath alwayes bene ſo obediente vnto him, euen to the death of the croſſe.</p>
               <p>The 268 day, Meditate how the voice of the Sonne of god is heard ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and produceth inceſſantly the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and diuine ſapience the which altho he did here on earth alſo, yet was he not eſteemed.</p>
               <p>The 269, day, Meditate how ſweetly our Sauiour taketh the fruition, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15411:80"/>ſweete influence, without any cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or intermiſſion.</p>
               <p>The 270, day, Meditate how Chriſt Ieſus in heauen doth enioy his kingly dignitie, beinge in earth ſaluted kinge of the Iewes in mockerie.</p>
               <p>The 271. day. Meditate how in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it is neither paine nor greife, to praiſe and laude god, and our Sauiour Ieſus, to wom it was no greife (for the ardent loue he had to mans ſaluation) to be contemned and mocked here on earth.</p>
               <p>The 272. day, Meditate with what glorie our Lord in heauen is compaſſed with Seraphins, who here on earth was compaſſed and inuironed with ſinners.</p>
               <p>The 273. day, Meditate what ioye of heart Ieſus hath now amonge the Cherubins, in recompence of the great affliction of heart which he ſuffered an earth a monge the multitude of the Iewes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:15411:80"/>
The 274, day, Meditate how Chriſt is now inuirened with the diuiue brightres and ioy, for on the earth he was compaſſed with ſadnes vpon ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when he did ſweate water and blood.</p>
               <p>The 275. day, Meditate how Chriſt feeleth him ſelf ſo much at eaſe, and ſweetly entreated, when he beareth the voice of his frendes ſweetly reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge in heauen for that on the earth he heard his enimies cryenge, we ſeeke Ieſus of Nazareth.</p>
               <p>The 276. day. Thinke how inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt is behoulden of his heauenly father, and of al the celeſtial courte, for that vpon earth he had ſo gently ſuffered, the vnworthie &amp; cruel coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his enimies, who ſo cruelly had pulled him by the heare of his head and beard.</p>
               <p>The 277. day, Thinke how ioyfully Chriſt is now elleuated and reſteth ſweetly in the throane of his heauenly
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15411:81"/>father, for that here on the earth, he lay miſerably vnder the feete of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and was ſpurned and troaden of them with great contempt.</p>
               <p>The 278. day, Meditate how ſweetly Chriſte reioyceth for that he is the only iudge of mankinde, who beinge vpon earth, was by them iudged to be whiped, crowned with thornes, and crucified, and yet wil be their merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully iudge.</p>
               <p>The 279. day, Meditate how god the euerlaſtinge father crowneth our Sauiour, with the crowne of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge glorie, who being on earth caried &amp; ſuſtained the moſt in famous Croſſe vpon his ſhoulders for the health of vs al.</p>
               <p>The 280. day, Meditate how Chriſt in heauen is clad with glorie and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes who on earth ſo wilinglie caried, the purple garment for mockerie, ſhame, and diſhonor.</p>
               <p>The 281. day, Meditate how his holie
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15411:81"/>members are moſte ſweetly vnited to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and doe giue ſo ſweete a ſmel, that al his elect are by the ſame refreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, who on earth ſuffered in al his members moſte greueous paines and ſorowes.</p>
               <p>The. 281. day, Meditate how Ieſus ſo ſweetely feeleth him ſelf now touchig his ſacred blood incloſed in his veines, who beinge on earth did looſe al his natural bewtie.</p>
               <p>The 283. day, Meditate how his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine face ſhineth in heauen, which ſeamed on earth to haue loſt al comely forme and beautie becauſe it was ſo chaunged and disfigured with ſtrokes and buffetts.</p>
               <p>The. 284. day, Meditate what deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſauour Chriſt feeleth continually proceedinge from his glorious huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, in ſteede of the filthie ſauour he ſuffered on earth, and cheiflie of the ſpittinge in his holie face.</p>
               <p>The. 285. day, Meditate how Chriſt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15411:82"/>is compaſſed on the right hand of his heauenly father with an innumetable multitude of Angels, who ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famouſly on earth was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged betwene two theeues.</p>
               <p>The 286. day, Thinke how by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites of his paſſion he doth obteine al the delightes aforeſaid, with diuers other innumerable merits, al which deſcend and flowe vpon ſinners, by the ſtreames and courſe of his mercie.</p>
               <p>The 287. day, Conſider how he drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wine of ioy and euerlaſtinge loue. who on the Croſſe taſted of the bitter gaule and vineger.</p>
               <p>The 288. day, Meditate how Chriſte feeleth him ſelf in reſpect of his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie being ſo high raiſed in ioy and gladnes, who being on earth ſuffered ſo many abuſes and diſpiſements.</p>
               <p>The 289. day Meditate in what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible reſte and ſweetnes the ſowle of Chriſte is in, aboundinge in al diuine delightes, which one the earth hath
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15411:82"/>indured ſo many bitter ſighes and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
               <p>The 290. day, Meditate with what ſweetenes Chriſt is now an hoſte to his elect, whom he feedeth and feaſteth with diuers amiable and pleaſant delightes.</p>
               <p>The 291 day, Meditate how loue hath opened the noble and diuine harte of Chriſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which iſſueth the noble &amp; ſweete wine, which maketh drunke al the inhabitants of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>The 292 day, Meditate how our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Champion Chriſt Ieſus ſhal retorne at the laſt day, to giue iudgement on the quick and dead.</p>
               <p>The 293, day, Meditate of the day of iudgement when the voice of the maieſtie of god ſhal be heard, which ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande the thunder, lightninge, windes &amp; death, to goe forth in their furie to the end that al fleſh ſhal die, for the day of iudgment approcheth.</p>
               <p>The 294. day, Meditate how the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15411:83"/>windes, thunder, and lightninge ſhal rore one againſt another wherby death ſhal come on al men for terror &amp; feare.</p>
               <p>The 295. day, Meditate in what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wrath and Ire the diuine iuſtice ſhal ſend his Angels fainge, <hi>goe vvith ſounde of trumpet and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l al people before me to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for I am novv readie, and vvil iudge al people accordinge to their vvorkes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 296. day, This day in Rhodes ſalute. S. Iohn the Baptiſt, and al the Parriarkes, &amp; Prophets, becauſe thou haſte now receiued great knowledge of their pomiſes and prophecies which they haue long ſince foretolde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>An Aduertiſement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>About this place of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en hapneth great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, by occaſion of which, followeth.</hi> 17. <hi>exerciſes of the iudgment and paines of the damned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate with what agilitie the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles doe flie out of heauen, &amp; deuide them ſelues in to the four corners and windes of the worlde, to aſſemble al
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15411:83"/>people, cryinge by the ſound of a Tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ariſe ye dead and come to iudgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. 297. day, Meditate how Chriſt wil appeare very terrible to al men, euen from Adam to the childe laſte borne; and euery one ſhal take his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per body, and aſſemble him ſelfe to the valley of Ioſaphat.</p>
               <p>The. 298 day, Meditate of the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and dreadful eſtate of ſinners cryinge: woe, woe, woe;.</p>
               <p>The. 299 day, Meditate in what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible manner the damned ſoules ſhal come out of helle, and ſhal take againe their ſtinkinge bodies, with noiſe, and terror moſte dreadful and terrible</p>
               <p>The. 300. day, Meditate of the poore ſoules remayninge then in Purgatorie not fully purged, and how that their horror, paine and affliction ſhal be augmented, and ſhal cleanſe them that they may be the ſooner deliuered.</p>
               <p>The. 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, Meditate how hard and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15411:84"/>inſupportable it ſhal be to ſinners, to heate that dreadful ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente, <hi>Goeyeecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into euerlaſtinge fire prepared for the Deuil and his Angels.</hi> And what a terrible thinge it ſhal be to heate the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to howle, roare, and lament.</p>
               <p>The. 302. day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Meditate what a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thinge the tuninge to and fro of the deuilles ſhal be amonge the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and damned ſoules.</p>
               <p>The. 303. day, Meditate of the great enuie and malice of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Deuils, who would not that any one perſon ſhould be ſaued.</p>
               <p>The. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>04. day, Meditate how vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge the ſinners ſhal be to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgment ſeate of the maieſtie of God, for that they certainly knowe their euerlaſtinge damnation.</p>
               <p>The. 305 day, Meditate with what great enuie the Deuil ſhal thruſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the damned priſons to goe to iudgment, and to make thier account of al their euil workes, wordes. and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15411:84"/>thoughtes, and to receaue the moſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bitter ſentence of the iudge.</p>
               <p>The. 306. Meditate how aſhamed the ſinners ſhal be when god ſhal giue the whole world to vnderſtand their euil deedes, and there ſhal ſee and clearely knowe, that they ſhal dwel for euer more in hel with the curſſed Deuilles.</p>
               <p>The. 307. Meditate what ſorrowe and anguiſhe the condemned ſinners ſhal be in, when they ſhal heare al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to conſent to their damnation. and that no man ſhal haue pittie, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compaſſion on them.</p>
               <p>The. 308 Thinke how vnwillingly ſinner, ſhal be to behould the face of the diuine Maieſtie, which then ſhal be very terrible, yet not with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge they ſhal be conſtrained to behould it.</p>
               <p>The. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>09, day, Thinke how the great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the damned ſhal far exceede the nomber of the ſaued: and how that many are caled, but few are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:15411:85"/>
The. 310 day, Thinke how horrible it ſhal be to the damned, that their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhal be euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>The. 311. day, Thinke and thinke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that there is not ſo litle a ſinne committed in this worlde, but ſhal haue in hell his perticuler paine, if it be not amended by penance.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>12 day, Meditate how god ſhal harden his hart, and be highly offended with ſinners and wicked perſons, when Iuſtice ſhal ſhut the gates of hell, and locke them in, which neuer ſhal be opened.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>Of the Ioyes of Paradiſe.</head>
               <p>The 313. day. Meditate what great ioy the Angells and al the elect ſhal haue, when they returne to heauen with great triumphe with their Lord and maker.</p>
               <p>The 314. day, Meditate how ſweetely al the ſaued ſoules ſhal reioyce, when they ſhal heare the ſweete and melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious worde of the Iudge, ſayinge.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15411:85"/>
                  <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father and poſeſſe the kingdome prepared for you before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the worlde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 315. day, Meditate what prayſes and thankſgeueing ſhal be yealded to god the father eternally, by his elect and ſaued creatures, for that by his grace he hath preſerued them.</p>
               <p>The 316. day, Meditate how the moſte excellent praiſe of <hi>Sanctus, Sanctus, Sanctus,</hi> is ſonge in heauen without ceaſinge. bleſſed be thou o Chriſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nally, that haſte redeemed and ſaued vs.</p>
               <p>The 317. day, Thinke how the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittes, and ſaued ſowles, do reioyce in behouldinge the face and pleaſant viſage of our Lord, out of which may be drawen alioy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>The 318. day, Thinke how al, ſaued creatures doe now reioyce in makinge ioy, beinge ſet at the heauenly table with ful delighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, perpetual reſt, pui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15411:86"/>and riches, and doe drinke of the aboundance of gods howſe, and talkinge of ſuch great ioy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie hath ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, care hath heard, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in to the harte of man.</p>
               <p>The 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 Meditate how god hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urning Seraphins, moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and incomparable faier ſhaning a houe al Angelical creaturs. And how the beutie of the moſt highe and holie Trinitie, ſhineth infinitlie about the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outie of the Seraphin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The 320 day, meditate how the roble Scraphins burning in the love of God, doe ioy without ceaſing in the diuine fulnes, in behoulding continually, the heauenly and moſt diuine iufluence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the father and his welbeloued-Sonne.</p>
               <p>The 321. day, Thinke how the noble Cherubins, haue there regarde amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie fixed on god, &amp; do admire of the excellent ſweetenes and influence, of his moſt noble diui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:15411:86"/>
The 322 day Thinke how much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is giuen to the moſt excellente Cherubins, whereby they haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theire Creator, and doe enioy the illumination of the moſt high di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie.</p>
               <p>The 323. day meditate how the Thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes doe reſt the ſelues quietly in God, and doe enioy a maruelous ſweetene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in him.</p>
               <p>The 324. day, meditate how all the happie ſpirits of the caeleſtiall Courr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abounding with innumerable &amp; ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable delightes, without ceaſing doe giue continual praiſe, to the moſt high and holie Trinitie.</p>
               <p>The 325. day, meditate how the holie Trinitie is the fountaine and increated nature, from whence al things doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, in forme and Creation.</p>
               <p>The 362. day, meditate how the holie Trinitie is the cleare glaſſe wherein all Saints doe behoulde and contemplate, the diuine power, wiſdome, &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15411:87"/>them ſelues alſo, and all thinges</p>
               <p>The 327. day, Meditate howe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without ceaſinge giueth influence ingenderinge his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in new delights of ioyes.</p>
               <p>The 328. day, Meditate of the perſon of the Sonne, who is the eternall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the father, being eternally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred and borne of his father, as a moſt ſhinning beame of the light of the Sonne.</p>
               <p>The 329. day, Meditate how the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god reioyceth al the heauenly citie, and geueth recreation to al the bleſſed ſpirites, who without any means, are vnited and conioyned with god.</p>
               <p>The. 330. day, Meditate how the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god loueth the Father, &amp; the Father the Sonne, and what great ioy the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hath in behouldinge his Father, and againe the Father in behouldinge his Sonne.</p>
               <p>The. 331. day. Thinke of the holie ghoſt
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15411:87"/>proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father &amp; the Sonne, &amp; how continually he filleth all them that are in heauen with the pleaſant ſappe of ioy, and entertayneth them without ceaſing with fre ſhe ioy.</p>
               <p>The 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2, day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>To S.</hi> Georges <hi>Churche in Venice vvhere is his arme and his hande.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate of the greate ioie that the Queene of Paradiſe and mother of god Marie hath at this preſent, of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that ſhallbe ſhewed to her euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in heauen of God, &amp; of al faued creatures.</p>
               <p>The 334 day, <hi>To S. Barb aras Church vvhere her body is, and a great bone of S.</hi> Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. Meditate how the ſweete flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Virginitie of Marie inceſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marueleth, for that the Creator of all creatures was ſo much humbled as to ſucke her pappes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. day, Meditate how the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God is now an Aduocatrixe &amp; a pacifier of al ſinns, before out heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, with her Sonne ſhewing hir
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15411:88"/>Virginall pappes, for the whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creatures which be ſaued; yeald therefore to her euermore praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and thankes-geuing.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>35. day, meditate how great the ſweetenes is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cie tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th now in the glorie of Paradice, for the riches of the nolie G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is opened vnto her.</p>
               <p>The 336. day, <hi>VVithin</hi> Venice <hi>vvhere thou art to recken vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th the Patron of the galley</hi> S Peter <hi>vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anie. If thou haſte ſatiſfied all thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed him in the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>date and giue him thanke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vvith ſome praier to his honour:</hi> Meditate vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy the Queene of Paradiſe hath being ſett nexte the moſt holy and glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>37. day <hi>To Palia.</hi> Meditate vvhat greate ioy Macie taketh in that ſhe hath bene the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting worde.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>38. day, meditate how ſweetely Marie lowlie gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkes to the holy Trinitie, and gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth thanks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15411:88"/>ceaſing, and knoweth perfectlie ſhe is beloued.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>9. day, Meditate how our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is ſweetely en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roned with holie Angels &amp; the heauenly noſte, and how her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rightnes and theirs compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hadow to the bright Sunne.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>40 day, Meditate how the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tels reioyſe in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auce, pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſered wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtarrs of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hining like the ſunne.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. day. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt where is the body of the Infance</hi> Simeon <hi>vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e vvas marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y the Infide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls</hi> meditate how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Apoſtels reioyced for that they ſhall be ſette of twelue ſeates iudginge al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nations of the earth.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>41. day Meditate how the holie virgins doe follow the Lambe of God clothed with long white robes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with cleannes and Virgintie.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day meditate with what f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roues the eſpouſes of the lambe who
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:15411:89"/>Virgin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doe carrie the ſinguler garland and Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of golde, (which is caled Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eola) ouer the faier Corone of the heauenly glorie.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>44. day, Meditate how hartely the ſpouſes of the lambe are beloued of the holie Trinitie becauſe that for the loue of him they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued, notanie white ſoptted or defiled.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>45. day, Meditate how the holy Virgings doe receaue of our lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the coller of golde with other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes for theire neckes, by moſte ſweete loue.</p>
               <p>The 346. day, meditate how the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarckes &amp; Prophets reioyce without ceaſing for that they ſee in glorie hi. whoſe death accompliſhed all which they did Propheſie of him.</p>
               <p>The 347. day, Meditate how ſweetlie the holie m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtyres doe reioyſe vvith our Lorde for that for the loue of him they haue ſhedd their precious bloode.</p>
               <p>The 348. day, Meditate vvhat compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15411:89"/>of holy Martirs with Palmes in their handes in ſigne of victorie and triumphe, proceede in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Holie Trinity and receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant treaſures of heauenly ioye and glorie.</p>
               <p>The. 349. day, Meditate how the holye Martyrs doe become dronke with the ſweete fountaine of heauenly comforts, for that they ſuffered ſuch bitter death for Chriſtes ſake.</p>
               <p>The. 350. day, Meditate how in the holie Confeſſors, the merites of their holie deuout thoughtes and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, is now brightly ſhininge in them.</p>
               <p>The. 351. day, Meditate how all the Saintes in Pardice haue done, no one ſo litle a good deede, but hath now his particular recompence and rewarde.</p>
               <p>The 352. day, Meditate how al the elect Sanites of god doe now tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe in Paradiſe, and are highlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:15411:90"/>there for al their labours.</p>
               <p>The. 353. day, Meditate how al the Saintes are comforted in heauen, for al their trauaile they haue ſo pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffered on earth.</p>
               <p>The. 354. day, Thinke how al the Saintes in heauen are now crowned with crownes of ineſtimable ioy, for that they haue here on earth behaued them ſelues ſo valiantly, in fightinge and conqueringe, the world, the fleaſh, and the Deuil.</p>
               <p>The 355. day, Thinke o Pilgrime for what life thou art created and made of thy creator. Wherfor behaue thy ſelf valiantly and fight manfully whilſt thou art here, for the life of man is but a war-fare on earth.</p>
               <p>The. 356 day, Thinke o deuout ſowle, to what holie and happie end thow art elected, for the which cauſe beare thy aduerſities with al patience, and ſuffer gladly here for a little time</p>
               <p>The. 357. day, Meditate of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraing
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15411:90"/>and cleare brightnes of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge life, and humbly craue that the ſame bleſſed brightnes may happpely ſhinein thy ſoule.</p>
               <p>The 358. day, Thinke of the moſt pleaſant ſweetenes of the euerlaſtinge life, and hartely pray that thou maiſt euen now ſomwhat feele and taſte the ſame, to the end that thy drye hart may be ſweetned and comforted ther with.</p>
               <p>The 359 day, Meditate of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte happie felicitie of the eternal life, and deſier with moſte earneſt harte that thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t haue comfort of the ſame, and be filled there with.</p>
               <p>The. 360. day, <hi>you may viſit at Colin the bodies of the. 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inges o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Saint Vrſula, and the</hi> XI. <hi>thouſand Virgin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Meditate of the life to come which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er to die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or wante of any thinge, and deſier of thy lord god that once thou maiſt behould and enioy the face of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te</p>
               <p>The, 361. day, <hi>you may viſit at Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:15411:91"/>Smock of the B. Virgin, the Hoſe of Sainte Ioſeph, and many other reliques</hi> Meditate hovv ioyfully one day God the Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r vvil giue him ſelfe to the povver of thy memory.</p>
               <p>The. 362. day <hi>At Maiſtrike is the body of Saint Seruace coſen to our Sauiour in the fourth degree.</hi> Thinke hovv ſvvetly they Sonne of God ſhal be vvholie encloſed in the povver of thy vnderſtandinge.</p>
               <p>The. 393. day, Meditate hovv comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Holy Ghoſte like runing ſtreames of vvater, ſhal be continualy povvringe in the deſiers of thy harte, vvith great and vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable ſvveetnes to thy ſovvle</p>
               <p>The. 364. day, Meditate hovv the Holy Trinitie ſhal aboun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antly fille thee vvith al kinde of heauenly delightes in his glorious kingdome of Paradiſe, yea vvith much more then either eie hath ſeene, eate hath heard, or the harte of man is able to conceiue.</p>
               <p>The 365. day, <hi>At thy lodginge in London, or from vvhence thou departedſt.</hi> Meditate hovv al faithfull Pilgrimes, after this mortal Pilgrimage, ſhal be in greate eaſe, reſt, and ſvvetnes for euermore, and ſhal remaine happie vvith out end. The vvhich, the Holy Trinitie, by the interceſsion of the Bleſſed mother, and of al Saintes graunte vs, Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15411:91"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
